<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soule is immortall, or, Certaine discourses defending the immortalitie of the soule against the limmes of Sathan to wit, Saducees, Anabaptists, atheists and such like of the hellish crue of aduersaries / written by Iohn Iackson.</title>
            <author>Jackson, John, fl. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14297a.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116566</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">39960804</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 39960804</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:3 or 1949:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soule is immortall, or, Certaine discourses defending the immortalitie of the soule against the limmes of Sathan to wit, Saducees, Anabaptists, atheists and such like of the hellish crue of aduersaries / written by Iohn Iackson.</title>
                  <author>Jackson, John, fl. 1611.</author>
                  <author>Houppelande, Guillaume, d. 1492. De immortalitate animae.</author>
                  <author>Xenocrates, of Chalcedon, ca. 396-ca. 314 B.C. De morte.</author>
                  <author>Athenagoras, 2nd cent. De resurrectione.</author>
                  <author>Palingenio Stellato, Marcello, ca. 1500-ca. 1543.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 183 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by W.W. for Robert Boulton dwelling in Smithfield neere Long [land?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title of first part reads: Guilermus Houppelandus: Of the immortalitie of the Soule.</note>
                  <note>Consists of translations or paraphrases of works of Guillaume Houppelande, Palingenius in Capricorne [sic], Athenagoras, and Xenocrates.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: 169 lacking in number only.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L8, M7.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1312:3 identified as STC 13850 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Bodleian Library and Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Immortality --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176301:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOVLE IS Immortall: OR, Certaine Diſcourſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the immortalitie of the Soule; againſt the limmes of Sathan: to wit, <hi>Saduces, Anabaptiſtes, Atheiſts,</hi> and ſuch like of the helliſh crue of Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p> Written by IOHN IACKSON.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>W. W.</hi> for <hi>Robert Boulton</hi> dwelling in Smithfield neere Long-lane. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176301:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176301:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER, Grace and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Arch-enimie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, <hi>Sathan,</hi> that olde Aduerſarie, as he dared to giue the aſſault vpon the Author of Saluation himſelfe; ſo hath he not reſted from the beginning, to lay battrie to the fortreſſe of Fayth, ſeeking by all meanes to beat it downe, and vtterly to raſe the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of it. And to this end, hath he not left vnſhaken any one article of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beliefe, both by old and new Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, the wicked inſtrumentes of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall warringes. So maliciouſly is he ſet againſt vs, that like a ramping and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lion, he goeth about ſeeking whom
<pb facs="tcp:176301:3"/>be may deuower: And where GOD hath his Church, be euermore adioyneth his Chappell, with his counterfaite, falſe, and faigned Religion, odious to God, and wonderfull to the world. Amongeſt the reſt, he hath not onely of old, but euen of late, battered the ſoule, yea euen the life of the ſoule of man: yea euen now doth he most ſtoutly batter it; by perſwading ſome, that it is corruptible and mortall; and putting into their mouthes the moſt venomed ſwordes of poyſoned ſophiſticall Argumentes to maintaine the ſame, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt certaine and neceſſarie trueth of the Soules immortalitie. For not onely the <hi>Saduces</hi> did diſpute againſt the immortalitie of the Soule; yea, and they in like manner, who ſayd in Saint <hi>Paules</hi> time, that the Reſurrection was paſt alreadie to him that beleeueth; and made no other reſurrection, beſides the reſurrection of the regenerate. But alſo the <hi>Anabaptiſtes</hi> of later yeares, doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:176301:3"/>the Soule to be immortall. And <hi>Paul</hi> the third of that name, Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> when he was breathing out his Soule and readie to die, ſayd; that now at length he ſhould try and know three things: Firſt, whether there were a GOD: ſecond, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Soules were immortall: third, whether there were a Hell or no; whereof all his life time he was in much doubt. Yea verily euen at this very day, there are now wicked <hi>Epicures,</hi> and graceleſſe <hi>Atheiſtes,</hi> whom the Diuell to lull them faſter a ſleepe in their ſinnes, and enforce them to heape ſinne vpon ſinne, hath ſo ſuggeſted them, that they are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that there is no rewarde for the Good, nor puniſhment of the Wicked; but that Man periſheth as Beaſt, and the Soule to come to nothing: according to that wicked verſe of <hi>Horace: Et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in nihilum, quod fuit ante nihil.</hi> For they affirme, that the Soule of man, like as of brute Beastes, is nothing elſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:176301:4"/>Life, or the vitall power, ariſing of the temperature and perfection of the Body; and therefore dyeth, and is extinguiſhed togeather with the Body. And ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſay, that the Soule ſleepeth, when the Body dyeth that is, is without motion or ſenſe, vntill the rayſing of the Body: which indeed is nothing elſe, but that the Soule is mortall; that is, a meere qualitie onely in the Body, which when the body is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, becommeth nothing; becauſe if it were an incorporeall ſubſtaunce, it could not be without ſenſe and motion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore hauing my ſelfe met with ſome of this badde ſort, and hearing of moe, I thought good euery way to fight in the cauſe of Chriſt Ieſus, with the weapon put in mine hand by my grand Captaine, and with might and maine, to heaw at theſe two Monſters, and vtter Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Soule. Therefore ſeeing that the print of the Penne may come vnto the eyes of moe, than the ſound of the voyce
<pb facs="tcp:176301:4"/>into the cares, I (by Gods aſsiſtance) haue ſet my talent on worke, againſt them both, proouing the contrarie: First, that the Soule is not (as they ſay,) mortall, but immortall: Secondly, that the Soule is not a forme, perfection, temperament, force, power, or agitation ariſing out of the temperature of the Body; but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce incorporeall, liuing, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, dwelling in the Body, and ſuſteining and moouing it. And this latter, is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued true by theſe Scriptures, Pſalm. 48. <hi>His Soule ſhalbe bleſſed in life.</hi> Heb 12. <hi>God is called the Father of Spirites.</hi> And it is ſayd of the faythfull; <hi>Yee are come to the Celeſtiall Ieruſalem, and to the companie of innumerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and to the Spirites of iuſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect men.</hi> 1. Cor. 2.11. <hi>Noman know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the thinges of a man, ſaue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of man, which is in man.</hi> In theſe, and like places of Scripture, both the Soule of man is called a Spirit, and the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:176301:5"/>of a liuing and vnderſtanding ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce are attributed vnto it; therefore it is a ſubſtaunce. And therefore to no purpoſe, doe the aduerſaries of this Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, oppoſe thoſe places wherein the ſoule is taken for the life and will of man; as Mat. 6. <hi>The Soule is more worth then Meate.</hi> Iob. 13.14. <hi>I put my Soule in my hand.</hi> For by the fore alleadged pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it is manifeſt, that this is not generall, but is vſed by figure of ſpeach; whereby we call the effect, by the name of his cauſe. Now for the former, that the Soule is not mortall, but immortall; and alſo for a further declaration of this latter, I haue tranſlated foorth of latine (for their ſakes that vnderſtande not latine) a certaine Treatiſe of the Immortalitie of the Soule; and thereunto haue adioyned other mens iudgments and reaſons, for the helpe of the matter, &amp; Scriptures confirming the ſame, and confuted the Aduerſarie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176301:5"/>
            <head>GVILERMVS HOVPPELANDVS: Of the immortalitie of the Soule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the auncient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers flouriſhed in Witte, and profited in Studie, it is no common opinion, but vnto all men a ſure and certaine perſwaſion: For by Studie and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, they on euerie ſide made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues away vnto thoſe thinges that are by Nature, almoſt incomprehenſible: And by their benefite, there are many thinges publikely left vnto all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which we are glad of, and doe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile at their inuentions. They meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the World, ſubiected Heauen to their Rules, ſearched out the ſundry cauſes of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176301:6"/>Nature; and in ſome ſort, with their eyes contemplated the Worke-man of all the World. But of the ſtate of mans Soule, and the Immortalitie thereof, ſundrie ſectes haue in their Writinges, left ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie opinions.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, that Soules are Mortall, and die togeather with their bodyes. Some doe ſay, that they are Immortall, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies remaine in a fixed ſtabilitie. <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuus</hi> affirmed, mans Soule to be a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour; <hi>Thales,</hi> a Moyſture; <hi>Empedocles,</hi> Blood; for hee taught, that the Soule is Blood infuſed in the Heart. <hi>Diogenes</hi> and <hi>Anaximenes,</hi> Ayre. The <hi>Storkes,</hi> whereof <hi>Zeno</hi> and <hi>Chriſippus</hi> are the chiefe, do ſay, it is a Fire. <hi>Democritus</hi> affirmed the Soule to be made by a certaine chauncing courſe of certaine light and round mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Ariſtoxenus,</hi> an Harmonie: <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophanes,</hi> a due proportion of qualities. The <hi>Saduces</hi> (ſo called of <hi>Sadoc,</hi>) denying both Honours and Puniſhmentes; and vniuerſally both Spirit and Angell, doc impudently ſay, that mens Soules are Mortall, and die togeather with their Bodyes. The <hi>Epicures</hi> alſo affirming the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176301:6"/>Soule to be Mortall, doe place the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Good, in Pleaſures. For <hi>Epicurus,</hi> who, (as it pleaſeth the greateſt men) did moderately vſe Hearbes and Apples, &amp; ſuch meane Meate, was afterward, by thoſe that came after, being a beaſtly and filthy companie, reproched with infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; for his ſottiſh vnbridled Schollers, fell into voluptuouſneſſe, and counted themſelues to be moſt happie, with the vſe thereof. All theſe, and many other moe, in the reckoning vp of whom, it is not profitable for vs for to ſtay, thought mans Soule to be Mortall. Whom <hi>Plinie</hi> ſeemeth to fauour, when he ſayeth in his ſecond Booke of his Naturall Hiſtorie that God cannot giue men Eternitie, nor call againe the Dead. And alſo many <hi>Romaines,</hi> (renowned both for fame and learning,) for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius</hi> in his ſeconde Booke of the Immortalitie of the Soule, ſeemeth to mocke the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>That old cuſtome of the</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>commeth to my remembraunce, who, as it is written, doe lend Money that it might be payde them againe in Hell;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were certainely perſwaded,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176301:7"/>that the Soules be immortall. Fooles are they to thinke, that they there, weare long Garments; as <hi>Pithago<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as</hi> beleeued them to weare Cloakes. Moreouer <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> (as <hi>Saluſt</hi> witneſſeth,) plainely ſaid that mens Soules were Mortall: and many others alſo; of whom it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to ſpeake particularly. Againſt whom it is ſayd in the ſecond Chapter of the Booke of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> The vngodly ſay, (as they falſely imagine with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,) our life is ſhort and tedious; and in the death of a man there is no recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; neither was any knowne that retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Graue: For wee are borne at all aduenture, and we ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as though we had neuer been; for the Breath is a Smoake in our Noſtrels, and the Wordes as a Sparke raiſed out of our Heartes: which being extinguiſhed, the Body is turned into Aſhes, and the Spirit vaniſheth as the ſoft Ayre: Our life ſhall paſſe away as the trace of a Cloude, and come to naught as the Miſte that is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen away with the beames of the Sunne, and caſt downe with the heate thereof: Our name alſo ſhalbe forgotten in time,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176301:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and no man ſhall haue our workes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: for our time is as a Shadow that paſſeth away; and after our ende, there is no returning: For it is faſt ſealed, ſo that no man commeth againe. Come therefore, and let vs enioy the pleaſures that are preſent, and let vs chearefully vſe the creatures as in youth, &amp;c. Then it followeth at the. 21. verſe. Such things doe they imagine, and goe aſtray; for their owne wickedneſſe hath blinded them. And they doe not vnderſtaud the myſterie of God, neither hope for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of righteouſneſſe, nor can diſcerne the honour of the Soules that are fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. And in the third Chapter: The Soules of the righteous, are in the hand of God, &amp; no torment ſhall touch them: In the ſight of the vnwiſe, they appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to die, and their ende was thought grieuous; and their departing from vs. deſtruction: but they are in peace. And though they ſuffer paine before men, yet is their hope full of immortalitie &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are alſo others, of euery ſect and nation, as well Poets as Philoſophers, in witte, learning, fame, and glorie, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176301:8"/>then the former, who ſpeaking more rightly of the ſtate of the Soule, haue taught, that the Soules of men are not diſſolued togeather with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes; but are immortall, or rewarded with eternitie: For <hi>Hermes</hi> talking in his Dialogues with <hi>Aſclepius,</hi> about the eternall Word, confeſſeth, that the Soules of men are immortall; and that the Euill are puniſhed, and the Good eternally rewarded. Goe to, ſayth he, Wee muſt now reaſon of the Mortall, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall way or manner: The feare of death, vexe and trouble many, being ignorant of the true way. And a litle after; When the Soule ſhall depart from the Body, then ſhall the tryall of his merite paſſe into the power of the great Iudge: and hee, when he ſhall ſee it to be iuſt, ſhall permit it to abide in places fit for it: But if it be vnrighteous, it ſhall be throwne downe into the great deepe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the ſtormes &amp; whyrlewinds of the Ayre, and the Water; and be ſnatched vp betwixt the Heauen and the Earth, and be heere and there toſſed, haled, and turmoyled in eternall paines.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176301:8"/>But in this, is eternitie hurtfull vnto the Soule, that by the immortall ſentence, it is tyed to eternall puniſhment. And thy Graunfather <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> O <hi>Aſclepius,</hi> ſaith hee, the firſt finder out of Phiſicke, to whom is conſecrated a Temple vpon a Mountaine of <hi>Lybea,</hi> about the ſhore of <hi>Cocodrilli,</hi> a man of a very godly life; is gone backe againe into Heauen.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Phareſies</hi> alſo and the <hi>Eſsies</hi> doe ſay, that the Iudgement of God ſhall come, and that the Soules of men be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall. <hi>Joſephus</hi> in his ſecond Booke of the Warres of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſayth this: It is a confirmed opinion amongſt vs, that our Bodies are corruptible, and that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them, is not perpetuall; but our Soules alwayes remaine immortall: And when they be loſed from their carnall bondes, as though they were deliuered, or ſet free from a long ſeruitude; ſo doe they foorthwith reioyce, and are caryed vp on high. The <hi>Phareſies</hi> alſo beleeued the ſame: which two ſectes, were beſt allowed of among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as the ſame <hi>Ioſephus</hi> affirmeth.</p>
            <p>And of the <hi>Eſſeis</hi> being put to torments,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176301:9"/>the ſame <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſayeth: They ſmiling in the midſt of puniſhings, and laughing thoſe to ſcorne that eſchewed torments, did conſtantly yeeld vp their Soules with a certaine hilaritie, as though they ſhould at length receiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe: And what is meant by that in the Sentences of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> that aſſure them that remaine content with good things, that they ſhall liue beyond the Occean, where is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto them a full fruition of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Ioyes? For there verily, (ſay they,) is the Region which is aggrauated neither with Raine, Cold, Heate, nor any Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; but the Occean orient and gentle blowing <hi>Zephirus</hi> is there very pleaſant. But for euill ſoules, they chooſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſtormy and wintery places, which are full of wailings, ſchrikings, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, of paines intollerable, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance is euerlaſting, and world with out end. According to this ſame intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the <hi>Greekes</hi> haue faigned, that for thoſe whom they call <hi>Heros.</hi> 1. noble and halfe Gods, <hi>Semidij,</hi> are ſequeſtrated the Ilands of the bleſſed, but for the Soules of the wicked, Hell is deſtinated, wherein
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176301:9"/>alſo they faigne, that there is tormented certaine <hi>Syſiphos, Tantaluſses, Ixions,</hi> and <hi>Licias:</hi> For the <hi>Greeke</hi> ſay, that <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and well deſeruing Soules, indued with immortalitie, dwell vp very high in the Ayre; whereof <hi>Jſiodore</hi> ſayeth: <hi>Heroas dicuntur a Junone traxiſse nomen. Grece enim luno a herba appellatur, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Heroas</hi> are ſayd to haue drawne their name from <hi>Juno;</hi> for in the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue, <hi>Iuno</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Herbe, and therefore I know not what Sonne of hers according to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> was called <hi>Heros,</hi> which Fable hath a miſticall ſignification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Ayre is deputed to <hi>Juno;</hi> where in they will haue <hi>Heroas</hi> to dwell: for when the Poet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill</hi> deſcribed the <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſean</hi> Fieldes, where they thinke the ſoules of the bleſſed Saintes doe dwell, hee did not onely ſet downe that thoſe do dwell there, that haue been able to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their owne merites; but addeth alſo, &amp; ſayth: Thoſe alſo that by deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, haue made others mindful of them; that is to ſay, who haue ſo deſerued, that by their deſeruings, they haue made others mindfull of them. Moreouer, as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176301:10"/>concerning the <hi>Greekes,</hi> Hiſtories doe make mention of two kindes of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: One, <hi>Italike</hi> of that part which in times paſt was called <hi>Magna Graecia:</hi> The other, <hi>Jonicke,</hi> of that part which is now called <hi>Graecia.</hi> The Prince &amp; chiefe of the <hi>Jtalke</hi> kind, was <hi>Pythagoras;</hi> of whom they ſay, that Philoſophie firſt tooke the name; who was of ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie among the Auncients, that by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall opinion, he couered and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all others ſentence, and was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enough for the confirmation of euery ſentence whatſoeuer, if ſo be any thing was taught, to be that that he ſaid. For writinges doe teſtifie, that <hi>Ferecides</hi> the <hi>Sirian</hi> ſayd, firſt, that the mindes of men are ſempiternall; who was indeed an auncient man in the time that <hi>Oeneus</hi> raigned: which opinion, his Diſciple <hi>Pythageras</hi> moſt greatly confirmed; who in the time that <hi>Tarquinus ſuperbus</hi> raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, came into that part of <hi>Italie</hi> which was called <hi>Magna Graecia;</hi> wherein the name of the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> flouriſhed with ſuch authoritie, that a long time after, no others ſeemed learned,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176301:10"/>
            <p>Of the <hi>Ionicke</hi> kind, <hi>Thales Miliſius</hi> was the Prince: a man very notably well learned and wiſe, and therefore ſo much the more admirable to his Schollers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was able by the knowledge of Aſtrologie, to foreſhew the Eclipſes of the Sunne and Moone. To whom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Anaximander,</hi> who left his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Anaximenes,</hi> the Maiſter of <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> and <hi>Dyogenes.</hi> After <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Arch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laus</hi> his Scholar: After <hi>Socrates</hi> aroſe, who by the Oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> was iudged the wiſeſt of all men, and left very many followers of his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie; whoſe ſtudie was chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the diſceptation &amp; reaſoning of Morall queſtions. After him, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed <hi>Plato,</hi> who, as <hi>Apuleius</hi> teſtifieth, was firſt called <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> but afterward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the largenes of his breaſt, he was named <hi>Plato:</hi> who was endued with ſuch an excellencie of Philoſophie and fineneſſe of Manners, that as it were, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the throne of Wiſed<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, ſeemed, by a certaine receiued authoritie to beare rule ouer all Philoſophers, both thoſe that were before him, and thoſe that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176301:11"/>were after him. Afterwarde aroſe his Diſciple <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> a man verily of great Witte and Eloquence, who farre excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many; ſucceeded <hi>Plate</hi> in the office of teaching: for this man ſhined vnto men as the Morning ſtarre, and enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the world with manifold preceptes, and ſundry beames of Philoſophie: and the miſt as it were, being wiped away from the eyes, repayred the mindes of men, that the trueth for euer might be continued among them. After the death of <hi>Plato,</hi> there ſucceeded alſo in the Schoole, which is called <hi>Accademia, Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus</hi> his ſiſters Sonne, and <hi>Zenocrates:</hi> and for this cauſe, both they themſelues, and alſo their ſucceſſours, were called <hi>Academickes,</hi> whom it pleaſed rather to follow <hi>Plato</hi> then <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſect of the <hi>Peripatetickes,</hi> becauſe that he was accuſtomed to diſpute walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: amongſt whom was ennobled <hi>Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, Porphyrius,</hi> and <hi>Apultius Afer,</hi> and alſo many other; of whom it is not deedfull for vs now to ſpeake in ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie.</p>
            <p>All thoſe therefore, whom with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176301:11"/>we doe ſee not vnworthily renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their fame, learning, and glorie, haue ſayd, that the Soules of men doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſtate of immortalitie: which ſentence <hi>Varro, Seneca, Saluſtius, Tullius, Boetius,</hi> and <hi>Macrobus,</hi> doe approoue. Hereof <hi>Tullius</hi> in his Prologue <hi>Super ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Scipionis,</hi> ſayth; <hi>Omnibus qui patriam ſeru<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerunt a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xerunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, certum in calum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitum eſse locum, vbi beati cuo ſempiterno fruuntur.</hi> Firſt, that for all thoſe that haue ſaued and enlarged their Country, there is a certaine place appoynted in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where the bleſſed enioy euerlaſting life. Moreouer, the Poets <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> and <hi>Ouid,</hi> thought the very ſame: For, in the fifth Booke of <hi>Metamorphoſis Ouid</hi> ſayth:</p>
            <q>—Morte carent animae, ſemper<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> relicta Sedenouis domibus, viuunt habitant<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> receptae.</q>
            <p>That is to ſay:</p>
            <q>
               <l>From death are free the Soules of men, and are immortall all:</l>
               <l>Which when their roomes they do for ſake and Corps doth dead downe fall:</l>
               <l>Then habitations new they haue, receiued by <hi>Ioues</hi> decree,</l>
               <l>Wherein he will for euermore,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176301:12"/>their dwelling place ſhall be.</l>
            </q>
            <p>All alſo, that thinke that Gods are made of men, or that men are tranſlated to the fellowſhippe of the Gods, haue thought the ſame. Did not <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Eſculapius, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> how they were deified and made Gods, ſay; The Idoles that you euery where worſhippe, were firſt of <hi>Egyptians</hi> called, Holy liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and their Soules worſhipped throughout all Cities, to whom they were dedicated while they were aliue? ſo that they are gouerned by their lawes, and named by their names, and in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner al Sectes and Nations are <hi>Attlanticks,</hi> as <hi>Libians, Egyptians, Frenchmen, Romaines, Spaniards, Perſeans, Chaldi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> Did not the great King <hi>Cyrus</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> doth witnes) ſay vnto his Sonnes when he lay on his death-bed: Doe not thinke, ô my ſonnes, that when I ſhall depart from you, I ſhall neuer be againe or be none at al? for al the while that I haue been with you, you neuer did ſee my Minde or Soule: you ſaw nothing but this Body that I beare: belieue therefore that I am, and ſhalbe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176301:12"/>although you ſhall not ſee mee.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, <hi>Galdisfa</hi> the <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the auncient elders of the <hi>Mahomets,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the traditions of their Law, doe beleeue and preach, that the dead ſhall riſe againe, and ſhall eate &amp; drinke delicate thinges, and ſhall haue many faire Women, which they ſhall embrace and vſe at their pleaſure: For <hi>Marcus</hi> declaring the conditions of the Eaſt Countries, ſayth, that the <hi>Tartarians</hi> doe ſo impudently deceiue themſelues, that if a Young man and a Mayde do die vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryed, they cauſe them to be eſpowſed and that very ſolemnly, before they be buried; that ſo in the life to come, they may more freely enioy their pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Touching <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> what he thought of the immortalitie of the ſoule many had rather doubt with the ſubtile Doctor, then raſhly to define: ſeeing that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe things that are read of him, whether they be thoſe thinges that hee wrote him ſelfe, or thoſe thinges that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay that he ſpake, his opinion can not eaſily be found out: for almoſt in all places of his doctrine, hee ſeemeth to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176301:13"/>fauour the immortalitie of the Soule: For in his ſecond Booke of the Soule, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the definition of the Soule, putting a difference betweene the partes of the Soule, he ſayth, that there are certaine partes that are not ſeparable from their Matters, or the thinges whereof they be made, or receiue the name: and ſome are ſeparable; as, <hi>Nauta a Nauj, <hi>The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner from the Ship,</hi> Vt rationalis anima a ratione:</hi> and therefore hee concludeth, that it is ſeparable from other thinges, as that which is perpetual, from that which is corruptible. And in the third Booke of the Soule, putting a difference betweene <hi>Senſus</hi> and <hi>Intellectus, <hi>the Senſe, and the Vnderſtanding,</hi>
               </hi> hee ſaith: <hi>Excellens ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile corrumpit ſenſum, excellens autem intelligibile non corrumpit intellectum:</hi> 1 <hi>The excellent ſenſible thing, corrupteth the Senſe; but the excellent intelligible, corrupteth not the Vnderſtanding.</hi> Alſo, in the firſt Booke, where the tranſlation that <hi>Auarroys</hi> expoundeth, the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doth ſeeme to bee a certaine ſubſtaunce, which is made indeed, and is not corrupted. And in his Booke, <hi>De
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176301:13"/>Animalibus,</hi> the Philoſopher enquireth, whether all Soules doe come foorth of their bodies? and hee anſwearing, ſaith: That it is not poſsible for corporall Soules to come foorth of the bodyes. It therefore remayneth (ſayth hee) that it is the Vnderſtanding that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth foorth, and only is diuine. And he in his twelfth of <hi>Metaphyſuks,</hi> ca. 8. ſayth: The moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſes as they were made before it, ſo doe they come foorth of it. And in the Booke of the death of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that he, lying on his death-bed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting his ſchollars concerning the feare of death, ſaid vnto them. <hi>Et vos, vt quid turbatis et de morte timetis? quae eſt via et inceſſus animae recedentis a corpore, et ad comprehendendum gradus diuinos, et coniungendum ſe animabus ſapientibus et letis:</hi> 1. <hi>And you, why are you troubled, and are afraid of death: which is the gate &amp; entring in of the ſoule departing from the body, to comprehend the heauenly wayes or degrees, &amp; to ioyne it ſelfe to the ſoules that are wiſe and ioyfull.</hi> After whoſe death, his ſcholers praied for him, ſaying
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176301:14"/>
               <hi>Deus qui recolligit animas Philoſophorum, recolligat animam tuam, et reponat eam in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauris ſuis.</hi> 1. <hi>The God that gathereth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather the Soules of the Philoſophers, gather thy Soule, and lay it vp in his treaſures.</hi> And <hi>Libro ſecundo poſteriorum,</hi> he reciteth <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſaying, That God doth thunder and ſounde as one that threatneth, that thoſe that are in <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> or in Hell, may be afraid. And in the 4. Booke of his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> hee ſayth: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſinne, yet they ſuffer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer puniſhment is layd vpon them; becauſe they ſay, that immortalitie is life euerlaſting: for the paſsion of life ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth immortalitie. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On the contrarie part, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth ſometime ſeeme to be againſt the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie of the Soule: for in his <hi>Praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> he ſayth: <hi>Corrupto animali, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſcientia, non autem ſcibile, ſcientia autem non est anima, ex quo videtur ſequi animam interire cum corpore:</hi> 1 <hi>The liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being corrupted, the ſcience or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is alſo corrupted; not the thing that may be knowne, for the ſcience is not the Soule, whereof it ſeemeth to follow, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176301:14"/>the Soule doth die with the Body.</hi> And in his Booke <hi>De longitudine et breustate vitae, <hi>Of the length &amp; ſhortnes of life,</hi>
               </hi> hee ſayth; <hi>The liuing creatures being corrupted, the ſcience is alſo corrupted, and likewiſe the healthfulneſſe; and therefore who of theſe ſhall reaſon for the Soule? for if it be not of Nature, but as ſcience in the Soule, ſo alſo ſhall the Soule be in the Body. And of the ſame another corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, beſides the corruption wherewith the corruption is corrupted with the Body: therefore it muſt needes be, that it hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body.</hi> And in the third, <hi>De anima: Non reminiſcimur poſt mortem corum qui in vita ſciuimus: <hi>We haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance againe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after, whom we knew, while they were aliue.</hi>
               </hi> And in the third Booke of <hi>Ethickes: Terribiliſsimum autemmors, terminus enim, &amp;c. <hi>Death is a moſt terrible and fearefull thing: for it is the tearme or end.</hi>
               </hi> And there ſeemeth thencefoorth to be vnto the dead, neither good nor euill. And <hi>Septimo Metaph,</hi> hee determineth of the Intention, that, <hi>Omnes partes quae poſſunt manere ſeperatae a toto, ſunt elementa; hoc ect, partes matcriales:</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:176301:15"/>All partes that may remaine, being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the whole, are Elementes; that is to ſay, partes Materiall. And <hi>Primo de Caelo,</hi> he ſeemeth to hold it for vnpoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, againſt <hi>Plato, Quod aliquid ſit factum perpetuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et incorruptibile, et hoc de mundo. &amp;c. <hi>That any thing can be made perpetuall and vncorruptible: And this is prooued of the world by two reaſons;</hi>
               </hi> which I omit for breuities ſake. And <hi>Quinto phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſico,</hi> he ſayth: <hi>Cuius est principtum, eius eſt finis: <hi>As is the beginning of a thing, ſo is the end of it.</hi>
               </hi> Out of which ſayinges, it ſeemed to <hi>Scotus,</hi> and to many others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was alwayes doubtfull of the immortalitie of the Soule, yea euen vnto the day of his death. And he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſometimes to come nearer the one part then the other; and ſometimes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to that, hee ſeemed before to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne; accordingly as the matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee entreated, was more conſonant to the one part, rather then the other. Yet notwithſtanding, by <hi>Scotus</hi> leaue, in the foreſaid ſentence, he ſeemeth to mee, not to differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his maiſter <hi>Plato</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and herein my witneſſe is <hi>Beſſario,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:176301:15"/>the Cardinall of <hi>Nicea,</hi> in that which he wrote in the defence of <hi>Plato;</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> alſo, whoſe teſtimonie amongſt all men, is moſt of authoritie, ſayth in the firſt <hi>Tuſculan</hi> queſtion: <hi>Post multorum Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopherum de animi quidditate recitatas opiniones, Aristoteles longe omnibus; Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonem ſemper excipio, &amp;c. <hi>After the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted opinions of many Philoſophers touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtioninges of the Soule,</hi>
               </hi> Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>is farre aboue all: but I alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> Plato, <hi>a man very excellent both for witte and wiſedome, and diligence, ſeeing hee embracing, receiuing, and allowing thoſe foure knowne kindes, thought that there was alſo a fifth Nature: The minde is equall for to cogitate, and to prouide, to ſpeake and to teach, and to inuent ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and to remember ſo many ſeuerall thinges; to loue, to hate, to couet, to feare: theſe thinges, and ſuch as be like vnto them, are not to be found in any one of theſe foure kindes, and therefore he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth there is a fifth nature, that is without name, and ſo hee calleth the Minde it ſelfe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Endelcia, quaſi quandam
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176301:16"/>contanuatam motionem et perennem: <hi>As it were a certaine continued and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting motion.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſpeaking alſo of the ſentences of the philoſophers, which we haue put in the firſt place, hee ſayth: <hi>His omnibus ſententijs, nihil poſt mortem pertinere ad quenquam poteſt; <hi>By all theſe ſentences, nothing can belong to any man after death.</hi>
               </hi> But of the ſentence of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> he ſayth afterward: <hi>Reliquorum ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſpem afferunt, poſſe animos cum e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus exceſs runt in caelum quaſi in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micilium ſuum peruenir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>The ſentences of others doe bring hope, that ſoules after they be departed foorth of their bodyes, doe come vnto heauen, as to their owne proper dwelling place.</hi>
               </hi> Seeing then, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſuppoſeth that the Soule is not of the nature of the Elementes, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth; &amp; alſo Saint. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the 22. Booke <hi>De ciuitate dej,</hi> but of that fifth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereof he will haue heauen alſo to be made: It ſeemeth contrarily, that as it is thought that Heauen is incorruptible and eternall; ſo alſo our Soules are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176301:16"/>and immortall; for either of them may very well be prooued with the ſame arguments that the other is: for euen as Heauen hath the nature of no Element; and neither heauie neither light, neither hath any contrarie: it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth then; that the Minde and Soule it ſelfe, like as Heauen, can neither be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated and bred, neither corrupted and brought to naught.</p>
            <p>Seeing then it is thus, that he thinketh an infinite multitude of thinges ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a thing impoſsible, hee might haue confeſſed with <hi>Pithagoras</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing that the Soule doth flit foorth of one body into another: for ſo had I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue him to thinke, then to beleeue with wicked <hi>Auarroys,</hi> who would haue but one onely Soule, and that to be common to and amongſt all men. And that ſame fellow <hi>Auarroys,</hi> although hee concluded with his Maiſter, that the Soule is immortall and eternall; yet in his ſecond Comentarie vpon the third Booke <hi>De anima,</hi> he playeth <hi>Ambidexter,</hi> and holdeth on hoth ſides.</p>
            <p>The vnderſtanding which is called
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176301:17"/>Naturall, as we haue ſayd, doth not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that ſometime it vnderſtandeth, and ſometimes not, vnleſſe in the reſpect of the forme of Imaginations, exiſting in euery <hi>Indiuiduum,</hi> or thing that can not be deuided: But in reſpect of the <hi>Species,</hi> kind, or ſort, it alwayes vnderſtandeth, vnleſſe humane kind doe fayle; which is impoſsible. Yet notwithſtanding, in this, he foulely erreth, not only againſt fayth, but alſo againſt Philoſophie, in that hee put all mens Soules into one Soule, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them all but one Soule, and would not that euery man ſhould haue a ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Soule: For he ſetteth downe three falſe and erroneous thinges, hauing no likelihood of trueth, but altogeather ſtrange from the minde and meaning of euery one of the Philoſophers. The firſt thing is, that the reaſonable Soule, is not <hi>Actus primus hominis, &amp;c.</hi> the firſt act of man, or mans ſubſtaunciall forme, giuing vnto him, to be, name, and reaſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man is, <hi>Hoc aliquid, <hi>This ſomething;</hi>
               </hi> but a ſubſtaunce, ſeperated, and a thing outwardly like vnto this. For hee ſetteth downe the vnderſtanding to be poſsible,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176301:17"/>ſeparate; which he calleth, the pure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall power in the kind of thinges that are intelligible. Secondly, he concludeth, that ſuch vnderſtanding, doth not come vnto man, <hi>a principio ſui eſse, <hi>from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his beeing,</hi>
               </hi> but then onely, when he is of yeares of diſcretion; for then is it in ſome ſort coupled vnto him, and continued, ſo that by it, he is able to vnderſtand. Therefore when he ſaith in the Fifth, that it is contimed in a Boy in his childhoode, and afterward in the 36. Now we haue found the manner how this vnderſtanding is continued in a Child, and ſeeke the cauſe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: But he ſetteth downe the manner of the continuance, when man by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined intentions doth concurre with the agent vnderſtanding, to cauſe the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the materiall vnderſtanding: ſo that to cauſe vnderſtandinges in act, hee calleth <hi>Abſtrahere, <hi>to draw away:</hi>
               </hi> but to receiue vnderſtandinges poſsible, hee calleth, <hi>Intelligere hominis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee concludeth, that all men haue but one vnderſtanding. Againſt theſe thinges, it is firſt argued on this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176301:18"/>wiſe. <hi>Anima eſt actus primus corporis or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganici phyſici, igitur anima est forma ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialis hominis:</hi> 1. <hi>The Soule is the firſt act of the naturall organicall body; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Soule is the ſubſtantiall forme of man.</hi> The antecedent is plaine: for the Philoſopher in the ſecond of the Soule, affirmeth, the Soule to be a Subſtaunce, and not an Accident. And afterwarde deuideth the ſubſtaunce into matter and forme, and compounde; and ſhewing that it is neither matter, nor compound; concludeth, that it is Forme, or the firſt Act of the bodie. &amp;c. Neither is it auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſay, that the Philoſopher ſetteth downe a common definition of the Soule, but ſpeaketh conditionally, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But if we muſt ſay that there is ſome common thing in euerie Soule; it ſhall verily be that firſt Act of a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall body. And that it is ſo, it is very plaine: for in the third Chapter, he ſaith: <hi>But of the vnderſtanding, nothing is yet manifeſt, but it ſeemeth to be an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of Soule.</hi> And then ſtraight after that clauſe, the Philoſopher ſaith. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſaliter dictum eſt, quid ſit anima: <hi>Wee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176301:18"/>haue vniuerſally declared what the Soule is.</hi>
               </hi> And an other Booke hath: <hi>Iam dixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quid eſt anima vniuerſaliter.</hi> And in the Chapter following, he ſaith. <hi>Sicut figurae eſt vna communis definitio, conueniens omni ſpeciei figurae: ſic et animae oportet eſse vnam definitionem conuenientem cuiuſlibet partium cius: <hi>As there is one common definition of a Figure, agreeing vnto euery ſeuerall Figure; ſo alſo ſhould there be one defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Soule, agreeing to all the partes thereof.</hi>
               </hi> Amongſt which, he expreſſely nameth the Vnderſtanding: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto he addeth, that ſuch a definition is that which he hath giuen; to witte, that it is. <hi>Primus actus. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is the ſeconde Allegation of any force; becauſe the Philoſopher when he ſaith: <hi>De intellectu aure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nihil adhuc mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtum eſt: <hi>As concerning the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there is yet nothing manifeſt:</hi>
               </hi> refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that Word, to a doubtfull premiſſe; to witte, whether euery one of the partes of the Soule be ſeparable, as it ſeemeth to the man that doth conſider it. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is euident, that the Soule is. <hi>Forma ſubſtantialis hominis: <hi>the ſubſtantiall forme
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176301:19"/>of man.</hi>
               </hi> Out of the twelfth of the <hi>Meta.</hi> in the Chapter beginning, <hi>Mouentes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem cauſae ſuperius allegatae:</hi> where the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher putteth a difference betweene the formall cauſes, and the efficient cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Alſo, ſo it ſhould follow, that a child, before that naturall vnderſtanding were coupled vnto him by the <hi>ſpices</hi> of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, ſhould not be a man neither endued with reaſon, and ſhould <hi>in ſpecie</hi> differ from an other man, and alſo from him ſelfe the elder he waxeth.</p>
            <p>Neither is the ſolution of <hi>Auerroys</hi> any thing auaileable, that man is taken <hi>dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer, <hi>in a double maner:</hi>
               </hi> one way, for the eſſence, by it ſelfe onely, compounded of the bodie, as it were the matter and the ſoule togeather, as it were of the ſpecify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forme thereof; which is ſometime called of the Doctors, <hi>Ratio particularis, <hi>the particular Reaſon:</hi>
               </hi> Sometime of the Philoſopher, <hi>Intellectus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After an other maner; Man is taken for a certaine Subſtaunce compounded of Man, <hi>Primo modo, <hi>after the firſt maner;</hi>
               </hi> and the Soule intellectiue, or the naturall Vnderſtanding: and ſo man is, <hi>per ſe vnum,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176301:19"/>
                  <hi>one by him ſelfe.</hi>
               </hi> After the firſt maner, a Child is not <hi>Homo, <hi>Man;</hi>
               </hi> of the ſame kind with himſelfe when he is old, nor with other men. After the ſecond maner, hee is not Man, neither endued with reaſon, <hi>Niſi potentia, <hi>but in power.</hi>
               </hi> Contrarily it ſhould follow, that a Child ſhould not be endued with Reaſon; neither Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly reaſonable: which is abſurde. Alſo, Man vnderſtandeth not, <hi>ſeipſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, <hi>not by himſelfe firſt:</hi>
               </hi> therfore by his ſubſtantial forme. The Antecedent is wel knowne, by experience: the Conſequent is plaine, becauſe the proper operation agreeing to any thing compounded, cannot be competent vnto it ſelfe <hi>per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am, <hi>by matter:</hi>
               </hi> therfore by the former, is the Soule the ſubſtantial forme of man. This is confirmed, becauſe then by no operation of an Animall brute creature, it could be conuinced, that the ſenſitiue Soule ſhould be the forme therof, giuing vnto it <hi>eſse, <hi>to bee;</hi>
               </hi> but the Aduerſarie might ſay, that it giueth it <hi>operari et non eſse, <hi>to worke, and not to bee</hi>
               </hi> Adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, that it is an expreſſe determination of the Church, in <hi>Clemen. Extra de ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matri:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176301:20"/>et fide Catholica.</hi> Againſt the ſecond, that the proper bodies, and all thinges ſhall returne againe vnto the ſame. But ſuch a continuation is not intelligible, but faigned, vaine, and vnprofitable: Becauſe that by ſuch continuance, man neither after the firſt maner, nor yet after the ſecond, could vnderſtand. Otherwiſe the painted Wall, or the thing wrought on the Wall, &amp; offred to the ſight, ſhould ſee; becauſe the colour that is on the Wall doth cauſe the viſion, and the ſight receiueth it.</p>
            <p>Againſt the third: It ſhould follow, that contraries ſhould be togeather in the ſame thing; for it is plaine, that in the vnderſtanding of one man, is Aſſent and Inſent: and in the vnderſtanding of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in the reſpect of the ſame, is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; Intent. And of that thing whereof one man hath Science, another hath one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Opinion, and an other Ignorance. Alſo according to this, we ſhould hardly vnderſtand nothing, but that whereof the Phantaſie ſhould cauſe Intention: But this is falſe; as experience doth prooue, by the actes aſwell of the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176301:20"/>as of the Will; and by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For the notice or knowledge Intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, is knowne by beholding or intui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiueely, &amp; is cauſe of the Notice reflexed.</p>
            <p>But of the immortall ſtate of the ſoule after death, the foreſaid Philoſophers are ſeuered among themſelues; for ſome ſet downe, that the ſoules when they doe depart foorth of the bodyes, do ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way enter into the bodyes of Beaſtes, correſpondent vnto their Merites: As for example; the Soules of Princes, into Lions; of Souldiers, into Bores; of others, into Swine; of ſome, into Wolues; of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, into Birdes and Apes, &amp;c. Neither in theſe, doth the paine and deiection ceaſe, vntill they had put on formes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to thoſe of the wild outragious Beaſtes: Whereof it came to paſſe, (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, in his Booke <hi>do bono mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi>) that ſome ſaid, that the chiefeſt good, or <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> of the great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, doth conſiſt in this, that their Soules, after their death, doe enter into Apes or Birdes. Others there haue been, that ſaid and affirmed, that they doe change their ſexe or kind, and doe turne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176301:21"/>vnto the infirmitie of Womans nature. Others will, that they goe into ſtrange humaine bodyes: as that fabulous Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of the <hi>Greekes</hi> doth witneſſe: for it ſheweth, that <hi>Menelaus,</hi> after that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbus</hi> was ouercome, laide vp his Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in the Temple of <hi>Iuno;</hi> which <hi>Panthoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> tooke away: whereof they ſaid, that the Soule of <hi>Euphorbus</hi> was entred into <hi>Panthoydes,</hi> and that he was <hi>Euphorbus</hi> himſelfe; whereof <hi>Ouid.</hi> maketh mention in his fifth Booke of <hi>Metamorphoſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ipſe egó nam memini Troiani tempore belli,</l>
               <l>Panthoides Euphorbus eram cui pectore</l>
               <l>Heſit in aduerſo grauis hasta minoris Atridae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is to ſay:</p>
            <q>
               <l>For I my ſelfe remember well, in time of <hi>Troian</hi> Warre,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Panthoides Euphorbus</hi> was my ſelfe, and deepe and farre</l>
               <l>A mighty ſpeare did pearce my breaſt which dead did downe me throw:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atreus</hi> mightie younger ſonne, did ſtrike this deadly blow.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And to ſpeake nothing of the reſt of the Philoſophers, <hi>Plato</hi> had the beſt iudgement, what becommeth of Men,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176301:21"/>if notwithſtanding (ſaith he,) they lead their liues righteouſly and holily, then ſo ſoone as the Soules are deliuered from their bodyes, they are receiued into the boſome of the Gods themſelues: But they being vnmindfull of ſupernall thinges, doe refuſe them as things connexed, and doe againe begin to be willing to enter into their bodyes againe. For ſpeaking of which out of <hi>Plato</hi> his doctrine, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill</hi> is very greatly commended: Therefore hee thought, that the Soules of mortall men, were alwayes able to abide in their bodyes; but through the neceſsitie of death, muſt needes be diſſolued: And that they are not able neither to endure perpetually without their bodyes; but thought, that by enterchangeable cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the liuing became dead, and the dead become liuing indefinitely and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. But in this, doe Wiſe-men differ from others; that ſtraight-way after death, they are carried vnto the Stars; &amp; that euery one reſteth very long in that Starre that is agreeable or meete for him: and at length, forgetfull of his old miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ouercommed with deſire of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176301:22"/>his body, returneth againe to the labours and ſorrowes of mortall men. Therfore by a moſt hard condition doth <hi>Plato</hi> make the Soules of men, yea euen of the wiſeſt, to be happie and bleſſed. Vnto whom are not ſuch bodies diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, as with which they may liue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and immortally; neither without them can endure in eternall puritie, but doe ſometime, though not immediatly, yet at the length, deſire to returne vnto the bodies: And ſo indefinitely doe by courſe, returne againe into diuers bodies, vntill the great yeare, in the which they ſhall haue againe their owne bodies, and all thinges ſhall come againe vnto their firſt eſtate. And thoſe that haue ledde a fooliſh life, hee thought, ſhould come vnto bodies due to their deſertes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Men or of Beaſtes: and ſo long to liue miſerably in them, vntill they be ſcoured from their filthineſſe, and their errours moderated, be redacted vnto the rule of reaſon and temperance; and ſo at length, deſerue to come vnto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their firſt eſtate. But <hi>Porphirius</hi> doth not onely remooue from mens
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176301:22"/>Soules the bodies of Beaſtes, but alſo will haue the Soules of Wiſe-men ſo to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the bonds of the bodie, that fleeing vtterly from euerie bodie, are kept bleſſed with the Father for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>It is a fooliſh thing to ſpeake of that life which cannot be moſt bleſſed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there may be a moſt ſure certaintie of the felicitie of it: and for the bleſſed Soules to deſire the blot of corruptible Bodies, and to returne backe againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; as though there needed a great Purgation, and an iniquination and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing to be required.</p>
            <p>Truely the ſentence of <hi>Porphirius</hi> is to be preferred before theirs, that will euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more haue a changing of bleſſedneſſe &amp; miſerie: Yet notwithſtanding, he will haue the ſoules of wicked men, to go into other humaine bodies, that they might be purged in them: And then when they be purged, without any returning to their old miſeries, hee placeth them in eternall felicitie: For it ſhamed <hi>Porphirius</hi> to ſay, that the Soules of men are poſted backe againe into beaſtiall bodies.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:176301:23"/>
            <p>If <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Porphirius</hi> had agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, I beleeue that they alſo ſhould haue ſeene that it is a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that Soules doe returne to their Bodies, and ſhould receiue ſuch thinges, as whereby they might liue bleſſedly and immortally: Becauſe according to <hi>Plato,</hi> the holy Soules alſo, ſhall returne to humaine bodies: According to <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirius,</hi> they ſhall returne to the euils of this world. <hi>Porphirius</hi> therefore may ſay with <hi>Plato,</hi> they ſhall returne vnto bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: and <hi>Plato</hi> with <hi>Porphirius,</hi> they ſhall not returne to euill ones. Therefore that the Soules may be bleſſed, euerie body muſt not be eſchewed; but a body pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and incorruptible, muſt be receiued; wherein they may more conueniently reioyce, then waile and lament in any that is corruptible: So ſhall there be in them no direfull wretchedneſſe and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie; which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill</hi> concludeth out of <hi>Plato,</hi> when he ſaith:</p>
            <q>Rurſus et incipiant in corpore velle reuerti.</q>
            <p>That is to ſay:</p>
            <q>
               <l>And loe they now begin, to haue a willing minde,</l>
               <l>For to returne ſo corps againe.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:176301:23"/>
            <p>So, I ſay, they ſhall not haue a deſire to returne to other bodies, ſeeing they ſhall haue bodies eternally with them, into the which they ſhall couet to returne. It is therefore a more honeſt thing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that which the Saintes and holy Angels haue ſhewed, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue ſpoken by the inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt, which the Meſſengers of Chriſt our ſauiour haue preached, which the bleſſed Apoſtles haue taught and written; to witte; That there ſhall be a Reſurrection of our mortall Bodies: or, that mens Soules ſhall once returne vnto their owne proper Bodies, and thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalls There now remaineth for vs, ſo far-foorth as the Lord ſhall vouchſafe to helpe vs, godlily and humbly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ſmall Talent, to ſhew, or to perſwade the Immortalitie of mans Soule, or the reaſonable Soule, whereby we haue ſenſe, moue, and vnderſtande. And this will we doe ſo much the more humbly, as we doe ſuppoſe it the harder to be done: for there is ſcarcely any trueth more obſcure, &amp; out of humaine ſtrength, or the principles of naturall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176301:24"/>Philoſophie more difficile to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; which certainely ought to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a worke hard and wonderfull. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is the greateſt thing that may be for the minde it ſelfe, to ſee and know the minde it ſelfe: For as the corporall eye doth eaſily ſee other thinges, but can not ſee it ſelfe; ſo our Minde doth not ſo eaſily, contemplate, or looke vpon it ſelfe, as it doth other thinges: For verily this force (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith in the firſt <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culan queſtion</hi>) hath that Precept of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo, in qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouet ſe quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſcat:</hi> 1. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery one mooueth, let him know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> For I doe not beleeue, that he gaue that Precept, to the end to haue vs to know our members, or ſtature, figure, or ſhape, but that wee ſhould beholde the puritie and dignitie of our minde. To know this therfore, cannot be any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but diuine and ſtrait. This Precept giuen of the GOD, could not belong to any ſharpe and cruell minde. Euerie one therefore, that is not content with the perſwaſions, and probable and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiue reaſons, in this obſcure, difficile and hard matter, which exceedeth, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176301:24"/>or goeth beyonde all mans witte; hee (I ſay) is worthy to be deſpiſed, and to be left vnto him ſelfe in the vaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of ſuch like reaſons: For the hard thinges of our Fayth, ought rather to be conſidered by the Oracles of the Fathers, then diſcuſſed by the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. For often times humaine ſenſe, while it ſeeketh the reaſons of certaine thinges, &amp; can not finde it, doth drowne it ſelfe in the gulfe of Deſperation: And when it ſeeketh to finde out by reaſon, the force of the Immortalitie of the Soule, it falleth (for the moſt part) into the bottomleſſe pitte of Deſperation. Therefore leaſt through raſhneſſe and temeritie, wee ſhould deſerue to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked about the foreſayd doubt, we will (God willing) aſſay to reaſon and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in three Concluſions, according to the ſentence and iudgement of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers.</p>
            <div n="1" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:176301:25"/>
               <head>The firſt Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ALthough the Immortalitie of the reaſonable Soule cannot be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, neither demonſtrated by ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall and euident reaſon; yet by probable reaſons it may apparently be perſwaded both to the ſaythfull and to the vnſaythfull. The firſt part is plaine; for <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in 3. <hi>de Trin.</hi> ſpeaking of the life Mortall and Immortall, ſaith: <hi>Hac vtrum caveat humana natura, nec parua est quiſtic; humanis quippe argumentationibus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anc muenue con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utes, vix pauci magno prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti ingent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, vacautes octo, doctriniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſubtiliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis crudite, ad indagandum ſolu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s animae im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ort<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>let<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tem peruenire potuerunt.</hi> That is to ſay: <hi>Neither is it a ſmal queſtion, whether humaine nature doth want this or no: for becauſe that they that goe about to finde out this by humaine argumentations, ſcarcely a few endued with good wittes, hauing ſufficient leaſure, and learned in moſt ſubtile doctrines, could attaine to the ſearching out of the Immortalitie of the Soule onely.</hi> By reaſon thus: We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176301:25"/>naturally know the reaſonable Soule in it ſelfe, neither intuitiuely nor ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractiuely, by a perfect and diſtinct knowledge: therefore we can not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and by effectual reaſon, conclude the Immortalitie thereof, which natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and neceſſarily doe follow it. The Antecedent is cleare, of the intuitiue: of the Abſtractiue it is plaine; becauſe ſuch a knowledge naturally gotten, doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe the intuitiue knowledge touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing. Secondly thus; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing demonſtrated of the ſubiect, is firſt and more according to knowledge, ſpoken or predicated of that thing by which it is demonſtrated, then of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect wherein it is demonſtrated &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for to bee. But it is not naturally, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euidently knowne vnto vs, that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie is firſt and more according to knowledge, ſpoken of any other thing then of the reaſonable Soule: Or that propoſition wherein Immortalitie is ſpoken of another, is not to vs former or more knowne then this propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; The Soule is Immortall. The Maior is plaine, becauſe the demonſtration is of thinges
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176301:26"/>former more knowne, and the cauſes of the concluſion. It is confirmed, becauſe this Concluſion, <hi>Anima rationalis eſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinabilis: <hi>The reaſonable Soule is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinable:</hi>
                  </hi> Although it be euident and knowne by experience, yet it is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable: therefore neither this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; This Soule is Immortall, becauſe it is neither euident nor knowne by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, is demonſtrable. The Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is plaine; becauſe that Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is immediate, then the which there is not another that is former, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall to conclude this, <hi>Homo eſt diſciplinabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, <hi>Man is diſciplinable:</hi>
                  </hi> For I doe not beleeue, that the Cauſe can be giuen why the Soule is Diſciplinable or Immortall; but that of it owne nature it is ſuch.</p>
               <p>For the perſwading of the ſecond part of the Concluſion, we haue excerpt three reaſons out of <hi>Cicero</hi> his firſt <hi>Tuſculan Queſtion,</hi> and out of <hi>Cato</hi> the elder. The firſt, he draweth from (as it were) a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and in-bred opinion of all men; but eſpecially of old auncients. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Argument he draweth from the hope and expectation of prudent and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176301:26"/>good Men. The third, he fetcheth from the nigh ſimilitude and likeneſſe of our Mindes vnto GOD: Afterward we will induce other familiar Reaſons. The firſt Reaſon that muſt teſtifie this trueth, is Antiquitie: which the further it was gone from the birth, and difference of progenie, the better peraduenture it did behold thoſe thinges that were true: Therefore (ſayth he) it is ſure, that old men haue a ſenſe and feeling in death; and that man is not ſo blotted out by the departure out of this life, that he ſhould vtterly periſh. And this to be ſo, may be vnderſtood by the Ceremonies vſed at the Sepulchres, Graues, and Buriall of the dead; where is vſed ſuch Rites to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, as if they were ſtill indued with moſt excellent Wittes. Neither would they haue worſhipped with ſo great regard, nor vſed ſo deuout Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnleſſe it had cleaned to their minds, that Death could not deſtroy all things: but is as it were the Guide, Captaine, &amp; Leader of woorthie Men and Women, that doe goe from hence into Heauen; and change this fraile, brittle, miſerable,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176301:27"/>and wretched life, for a life permanent, euerlaſting, bleſſed, and ioyfull. From which opinion it is ſprung, that many (whoſe names it is not now needfull to reckon vp or rehearſe) are, for their good life and virtuous behauiour, while they liued heere in this world amongſt men, counted after their death, amongſt the number of the Gods. This ſame may hereof be vnderſtood, that all men haue a care, that theſe thinges ſhould be after their death; to witte, Propagation of Name, Procreation of Children, Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sonnes, and fulfilling of Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; with many other thinges. It is a moſt great Argument amongſt the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Why wee ought to beleeue that there is Gods; although there be no Nation ſo ſauage and outragious, whoſe minde is not indued with opinion of Gods. If any one would haue this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reduced, and brought vnto that ſtrait forme of Logicke wherein it ſhall haue leſſe force, they ſhall ſummarily haue it thus: All men, and eſpecially thoſe old ones, who as they ſeeme to haue excelled vs in ſtature of body, ſo alſo in excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176301:27"/>of witte; becauſe they found out all good Artes, (which was an hard thing to doe) iudged by nature, or were natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclined to iudge, that the Soules of men be Immortall: Therefore the Soules of men are Immortall. The Antecedent plainely appeareth to be true, of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that all men vſe about their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres or Graues, about the propoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their name, fame, and glorie; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the generation of Children, adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sonnes, &amp; of many other thinges, which men would not doe, vnleſſe they were naturally enclined to iudge, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be departed out of this life, there belongeth ſomething vnto them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they haue a naturall appetite.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe that <hi>Plato</hi> (whoſe authoritie is of ſuch force with <hi>Cicero,</hi> that he counteth him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be beleeued in what he ſaith, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſhew no reaſon why,) writing vnto <hi>Dioniſius</hi> in that Epiſtle that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Audiui ex Archidomo,</hi> doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, ſaying; <hi>Natura fieri viaemus, vt ignauiſsimus quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nihil curet, quae ſit de eo futura opinin. Sapientes auten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> et boni viri
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176301:28"/>cuncta faciunt, quo futura ſecula bene deſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimant:</hi> 1. <hi>Wee ſee that it commeth to paſſe by nature, that euery ſlouthfull ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, taketh no care what opinion ſhall hereafter he had of him: But wiſe and good men, doe all thinges whereby the ages to come, may thinke well of them.</hi> Whereby, I doe coniecture, that his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that they that be dead, haue ſome ſenſe, feeling, or knowledge of our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or the thinges that we doe. This Reaſon, <hi>Cato</hi> the elder following, doth thus reaſon in <hi>Cicero</hi> his Booke <hi>De Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nectute. Nemo vnquam mihi Scipio, perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debit aut patrem tuum, &amp;c. <hi>There ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any man perſwade mee;</hi>
                  </hi> Scipio, <hi>that either your Father</hi> Paulus, <hi>or your two Graundfathers</hi> Paulus <hi>and</hi> Affricanus; <hi>or that</hi> Affricanus <hi>Father, or his Vncle, or many other excellent men; whom now it is not needfull to reckon vp, did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ſo great thinges, which might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to memorie of their poſteritie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they did ſee very well in their minds, that the poſteritie ſhould pertaine vnto them: Or doe you thinke (that I may glorie ſomewhat of my ſelfe, as it is the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176301:28"/>maner of old men to doe,) that I would haue taken vpon mee ſo great labours both night and day, at home and in warre, if I were perſwaded that my glorie ſhould end with my life: Had it not been a great deale better for mee to haue ſpent my time in eaſe and quietneſſe, without any labour and contention:</hi> This ſpeach <hi>Cicero</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling more largely in the firſt <hi>Tuſculan queſtion,</hi> ſayth. <hi>Quae natura in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num genere melior, quam eorum, qui ſe natos ad homines iuuandos, tutandos, conſeruandos arbitrantur, etiam vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad mortem fortiter ſuſtinendam. Quis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſapiens ſine ſpe immortalitatis ſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferret ad mortem? Quid enim impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius, quam ſine vſto premio, ſe et vita et virtute propria priuare? Cum aut ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis aut egeſtatis labores, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>What Nature in Mankind can be better, then theirs, that thinke them-ſelues to be borne vnto this end, to the intent that they may helpe, defend, and preſerue men, yea euen vnto the abyding of the bitter bruntes of direfull death. But what wiſe-man wil of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelfe vnto death, without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176301:29"/>immortalitie: for what part can a man play more vnwiſely, then without any rewarde, to depriue himſelfe of life, and his owne proper vertue: when be might, with the reſt of the Citizens, patiently abide the labours either of ſeruitude, or of pouertie: Who will affirme, that Glorie doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the dead, if they haue no ſenſe or feeling of it: What good can this glorie doe to thoſe famous worthy men, ſo diligently &amp; notably cammended &amp; deſcribed of</hi> Poets, <hi>if ſo be they doe know nothing of it? Whether is it our partes then, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all thoſe worthy men of fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who haue valiantly ſuſteyned death for their Countrey; or to beleeue that they looked for the immortalitie of their ſoules? whoſe mindes, ſentence, and iudgement, to finde fault withall, or to reprehend, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to come the neareſt vnto temeritie or roſhneſſe.</hi> This Reaſon diffuſedly handled, may be brought to forme, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a double maner. Firſt, wiſe and good men, doe iudge and hope, that their Soules ſhall be immortall: therefore it is ſo. The Antecedent is very plaine: for otherwiſe they would not haue ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176301:29"/>them-ſelues, nor willingly died, that their valiantneſſe might be left to them memorie of poſteritie, vnleſſe they iudged that the poſteritie did belong to them. The Conſequent is plaine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the diuinations and opinions of good men are ſeene, as well as of the wicked. The ſecond, If the Soule were not immortall, no man (in his right minde) would offer himſelfe to death for his Countrey, or the Commonweale; nor yet ſuſtaine death for his Friendes. The Conſequence doth not ſeeme falſe: For the Philoſopher ſayth in the ninth Booke of <hi>Ethickes, <hi>That euerie one ought to ſuffer for his friendes; yea &amp; to die for them alſo, it need ſo required.</hi>
                  </hi> The ſame he ſaith in the 3. Booke of <hi>Ethicks.</hi> The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is plaine; becauſe none (that is in his right wittes) ought by good reaſon to depriue himſelfe of the chiefeſt good, or without hope to get ſome good thing either in this preſent life, or in that which is to come. But if the Soule be mortall, then it doth by death, depriue it ſelfe of the chiefeſt good, yea of all good thinges, without any hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176301:30"/>It may be thus confirmed: Death doth not profite of it ſelfe, or by it ſelfe, to the conſeruation of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, but is indeed againſt it: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if the Soule be mortall, and is not to be rewarded in time to come; then no wiſe man ought to ſtand to the trueth in the right of his Countrey, euen vnto death. The Antecedent is plaine, <hi>Simile est de vno ciue, et multis: <hi>What is the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of one Citizen, is alſo the duetie of many.</hi>
                  </hi> But it is a fooliſhneſſe to ſay; that all Citizens ought to die for the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Weale publicke, ſeeing that the Publicke weale is the life of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: For what profited them the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacie of the <hi>Saguntines</hi> vnto the ſafetie of the Common-weale? If the <hi>Saguntines</hi> would haue choſen the ſafetie of their Common-weale, they ſhould either haue forſaken their Fayth, or elſe neuer haue made ſuch Oth: But if they muſt needes keepe their Fayth, then muſt they needes looſe their Common-weale; as it came to paſſe. Secondly, the Conſequence is plaine. No man of ſound reaſon, ought to ſuſteyne a great euill, vnleſſe it be to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176301:30"/>eſchew a greater euill; or for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a greater good, then that good is, whereof by ſuch euill he is depriued; becauſe that of two euils, the leſſe alway is to be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if the Soule be mortall, and after death haue no beeing; then no ſuch good can be giuen, or be imagined.</p>
               <p>Neither doth it auaile, that <hi>Scotus</hi> ſaith, alleadging the Philoſopher in the ninth of the <hi>Ethickes,</hi> that hee that dyeth for his Countrey, giueth to himſelf great good, by exerciſing that great act of vertue. <hi>Et hoe bono priuaret ſe, omnino vic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe viueret: <hi>Hee ſhould depriue himſelfe of that good thing</hi>
                  </hi> (ſayth <hi>Scotus,</hi>) <hi>and ſhould liue vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, or in reproch and defame.</hi> If the Soule be mortall, there can not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dead, either good or euill, or ſenſe: For what can either prayſe, or fame, or glorie, profite the dead, if the dead know not of them? for after their death, they cannot giue vnto themſelues for the ſaid worke, either reward, ioy, or reioycing; for theſe are the affections of the minde.</p>
               <p>Neither againe is that true, or by any meanes to be receiued as true, or for any colour of trueth, which the ſame <hi>Sootus</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:176301:31"/>ſaith, that, <hi>Poteſt dari co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune bonum, propter quod debet ſe exponere morti: et totum bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exponere deſtructioni ſimpliciter, etiamſineſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immortalem: <hi>There may be giuen a common good, for whoſe ſake euery one ought to offer himſelfe to death: and what good ſoeuer he hath, to endanger it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſimply, although he can not tell whether the Soule be Immortall or no.</hi>
                  </hi> Becauſe it is not certaine whether the common good be alway rather to be choſen, then the particular and proper good. Yea, this is vniuerſally true at no time, but then when the particular good is included in the common good: But where the common good includeth the particular good, who is there of ſound iudgement, and in his right minde, that loueth the particular and proper good, more then the common. For the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher ſaith in the 8. <hi>Eth. Amabile quidem bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, &amp;c. <hi>Euery one loueth his owne good: therefore by good reaſon, euery one loueth his owne, better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other mans.</hi>
                  </hi> And 9. <hi>Eth. Amabilia ad alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> menſurantur, ex his quae ſunt adſeipſum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Louely things are meaſured vnto another, by thoſe things
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176301:31"/>which a man loueth him ſelfe.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Reaſon (becauſe I ſtudie to be ſhort:) The Soule of man, according to the moſt excellent operations, is like vnto God: And therefore of ſome it is beleeued, to haue a diuine nature. But of men of our Religion, it is called, The image of God: Therefore it is to be eſteemed like vnto him in immortalitie. The Antecedent is plaine, and very well knowne a confeſſed trueth amongſt all. The Conſequence is prooued out of <hi>Plato,</hi> alleadged by <hi>Euſebius Praeparationis Euangelicae, lib. 11. cap. 14.</hi> where are reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe wordes of <hi>Porphirius,</hi> handling this Reaſon. <hi>Firmam cortam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rationem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eam Plato putauit, quae a ſimilitudine <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vim accepit. Nam ſi Deo immortali ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis est anima, quomodo etiam ipſae ſicut exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar ſuum immortalis non erit?</hi> Plato <hi>think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that to be a firme and ſure Reaſon, which taketh force from the ſimilitude of ſome thinges: for if the Soule be like to God that is Immortall; how ſhall not then it ſelfe be Immortall, like as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amplar:</hi> I paſſe ouer the reſt. Which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as the ſame <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith) is drawne
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176301:32"/>out of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who firſt taught that the Soule is Immortal, becauſe it is the Image of God: yea, hee affirmeth, that aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is the Image of God. Whom the Wiſe-man following in the 2. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Booke of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> doth moſt briefely touch the ſame Reaſon, ſaying. <hi>Deus creauit hominem ineſtimabilem, ad imaginem ſimilitudinis ſuae fecit illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> 1. <hi>God created Man ineſtimable, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corruption; and made him after the Image of his owne likeneſſe.</hi> This Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo <hi>Saluſt</hi> toucheth in the beginning of his Booke of <hi>Catalines</hi> Conſpiracie, where he affirmeth, <hi>Animum nobis cum dijs communem, et virtutem claram, et aeternam: <hi>That we haue a minde common with the Gods, and a cleare vertue, and eternall.</hi>
                  </hi> Which Sentence, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Warre of <hi>Iugurtha,</hi> hee vſeth againe. <hi>Ingenij egregia facinora ſicuti et anima, immortalia ſunt; id eſt, <hi>The worthy workes of the Witte, like as the Soule, are Immortall.</hi>
                  </hi> Which alſo may thus be perſwaded. Theſe Actes to will, to vnderſtand, to remember, to loue, to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176301:32"/>hate, wherein the Soules haue conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie with God and Angels; may both bee, and be exerciſed without the body: therfore it is not repugnant to the Soule, both to bee, &amp; to liue without the body. The Antecedent is well knowne; and the Conſequent is plaine: becauſe the Accidentis not more abſtract then the Subſtaunce, from which it is ſayd to flow. Seeing then we doe prooue in our ſelues, that the Soule exiſting in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, doth know many thinges, which can not fall vnder our ſenſe; and that without the mediation or vſing the meanes of the body: (for wee prooue or finde by experience, that it knoweth the relations following Nature, and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible relations of reaſon: wee finde by experience, that it aſſenteth to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plections without poſsibilitie of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting, or erring, &amp; many other things:) ſeeing therefore (I ſay) that theſe Actes haue no conueniencie, neither can agree to other formes and thinges corruptible, it is moſt like and agreeable to reaſon, that theſe Actes are ſufficient to prooue, that the Soule is immortall. Moreouer,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176301:33"/>the Immortalitie of the Soule, is prooued by certaine reaſons of the Schoole Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors. Firſt: In whom there is power and virtue alwayes, <hi>Proficere,</hi> to <hi>profits:</hi> in the ſame alſo, there is power and virtue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to bee. Seeing that the ſubſiſtence of the Accident cannot be naturally without the Eſſence of the ſubiect. But in the Soule there is alway power and virtue, <hi>proficere, <hi>to profits:</hi>
                  </hi> therefore there is in the Soule, power and virtue alwayes to bee. The Minor is euident, by the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a certaine Wiſe man, who ſayth. <hi>Cum conſummauirit homo, tunc incipit:</hi> 1. <hi>When man ſhall make his ending, then is his beginning.</hi> And in an other place. <hi>Multitudinem ingreſsus ſaepientiae quis intellexit? <hi>Who hath euer knowne the multitude of Wiſedomes entries:</hi>
                  </hi> Which ſpeach ſeemeth to haue this ſenſe, that by the proſecting and increaſing of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the entrance in vnto her is multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; becauſe he ſeemeth more and more to enter in vnto her, that more and more profecteth in her. This Expoſition is helped by the ſpeach of the Prophet that ſaith to his Soule: <hi>Poſt me ingredi non
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176301:33"/>ceſsabis: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ceaſe to enter in after mee.</hi>
                  </hi> The Anſwere of <hi>Plato</hi> doth alſo further it: For he being asked, when a man can haue profited ſo much in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, that there can remaine nothing for him to know more; or when he can haue learned ſo much, that there can be nothing left for him to learne? Hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>Hoc ſolum ſcio, quod neſcio:</hi> 1. <hi>This onely I know, that I know not.</hi> As if hee ſhould haue ſayd, <hi>Solum cognoſco ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam meam:</hi> 1. <hi>I know onely mine igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> This I thus confirme. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and diſpoſitions that the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Soule can acquire or get, are not limitted: therefore the life of the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Soule, or the exiſtence thereof, is not limitted; and ſo by conſequence, it muſt needes be Immortall. The Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent is plaine; becauſe the Soule cannot know ſo many things, but it may know more. The Conſequence is plaine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is vnpoſsible for the virtue and power of euerie ſubiect, to be of thoſe diſpoſitions and perfections from the which the ſubiect is naturally prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: For this mortall life cannot ſuffice
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176301:34"/>naturally for the getting or participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of infinite perfections, ſeeing that euery one of them requireth time.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Reaſon is this: If the Soule ſhould be corrupted, and ſo mortall, it ſhould be either through the action of the contrarie; or elſe through the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſubiect. But it is not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by meanes of the action of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; becauſe it hath no contrarie. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be corrupted, by reaſon of the corruption of the ſubiect: becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is corrupted in that, wherein it conſiſteth by it owne perfection: For theſe are contrarie mutations; to witte, of Corruption, and Perfection. But the Perfection of the Soule, conſiſteth in a certaine abſtraction from the Body: for the Body waxing old in men, liuing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately and temperately, the Soule is perfected, according to the ſcience and knowledge thereof, and according to the virtues thereof. According to the ſcience and knowledge; becauſe in aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient old men, is Wiſedome; and in much time, is Prudence. According to the Virtues; becauſe ſuch men, are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176301:34"/>neither giue place to wicked Concupiſcence, nor haue any great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie in act. But young men, haue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Concupiſcences, and are delighted therein: neither can they refraine them, without great difficultie. This Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is confirmed by a double Reaſon. The firſt is this: That when the Body is weakened, or ſome Organ thereof hath receiued ſome hurt, the Soule is more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified thereby, and made more ſtronger and virtuous in the other ſenſes and powers, as though it were vnto them a more inward ſupply of thoſe thinges that ſeeme to be taken away by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the members: Therefore, when the Body dieth, the Soule doth not die. The Antecedent is knowne to be true, by experience: for a blind man is more ſharpe &amp; quicke in hearing and in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and in other ſenſes, then hee that is well ſighted. Whereof <hi>Guilermus Pariſienſis</hi> ſayth; That a certaine Blinde man was ſo cunning, and had ſo much proſited in experience, that he could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly tell onely by the touching, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, feeling, or croping, any peece of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176301:35"/>Monie of his owne Country coyne, though there were neuer ſo many and ſundry ſortes of them. And a certaine blind Boy in the fourteenth yeare of his age, learned all liberall Artes, knew and vnderſtood all the ſacred Scriptures, and taught them, and wrote moſt largely and amply vpon them; as is mentioned in the <hi>Tripartue</hi> Hiſtorie.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Confirmation is thus. As is the whole Body to the whole Soule, ſo are the partes of the Body, to the parts of the Soule. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one part, or ſome Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of the Body is corrupted, there is no part of the Soule corrupted, nor hurt, nor ſuffereth in it ſelfe; but remayneth ſound and perfect: Therefore when the Body dyeth, the Soule doth not die. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent is plaine by the Philoſopher: <hi>Si ſenex haberet oculum neuenis, videret vtig<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vt iuuenis, &amp;c. <hi>If an old man ſhould haue the eye of a young man, hee ſhould ſee as a young man:</hi>
                  </hi> therefore when part of the Body is hurt, the Soule is not hurt in it ſelfe, although it be depriued of the act. For when our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> reſtored ſight vnto the blind, he gaue not, nor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176301:35"/>conferred vnto the Soule any ſtrength or actiuitie; but onely repaired the hurt, or indiſpoſition of the Organ. Alſo the reaſonable Soule, by how much more it vnderſtandeth and knoweth thinges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, by ſo much more perfect is it made, and more diſpoſed to vnderſtand. But the Soules of all mortall men, by how much more they feele and exerciſe their operations, by ſo much more are they weakened, &amp; made vnfit for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing of their operations. Experience doth teach both theſe, to be true: and ſo doth the Philoſopher alſo, where hee ſaith. <hi>Excellens ſenſibile currumpit ſonſum; excellens autem intelligibile non corrumpit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum:</hi> 1. <hi>The excellent ſenſible thing corrupteth the ſenſe: but the excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible thing doth not corrupt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> Therefore there is another kind of the Soule, from that which is corruptible; and ſo by conſequence, it muſt needes be Immortall.</p>
               <p>Morcouer, the formes or Soules, which all men iudge, or do thinke to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, &amp; to be of themſelues wholly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and the corruption of the whole
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176301:36"/>to be as is the corruption of the part, are corrupted as the part is corrupted: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are extended, hauing part without part; and are greater in a great body, and leſſer in a leſſe body. This <hi>Scotus</hi> doth very notably deduct in the fourth Booke; That in Nutrition, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a new forme; and in the Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution there floweth not onely the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but alſo the thing compounded of the matter and the forme: Therefore the Nutrition or Nouriſhing, is called a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And it is very manifeſt, that in Nutrition, there are more partes of the matter in the whole, then was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; or elſe the new part of the matter is in the whole without forme: which is not to be graunted neither vnder the whole forme, becauſe ſo it is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, hauing part without part; or elſe vnder a new forme, and ſo we haue our purpoſe: or elſe vnder part of the forme that was before; and then euen that, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth off to perfect part of the matter, which before it perfected: and ſo one and the ſame part of the materiall forme, ſhall ſlit from one part of the matter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176301:36"/>to an other part, which is inconuenient: or that part of the forme, being the ſame it was before, doth in like maner perfect part of the matter that it did before; and this part of the matter, now new: And ſo it ſhall togeather perfect two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectable thinges; either whereof, is fully matchable to it ſerfe. But the reaſonable Soule, is not extended or ſtretched out; neither greater in a greater body, &amp; leſſer in a leſſer Body: but it is whole in the whole Body, and wholly or altogeather indiuiſible in euery part: therefore it is an other kind from the corruptible formes, and mortall Soules.</p>
               <p>It is a thing well knowne, that all men doe deſire bleſſedneſſe; and that it is the end of good men. It is alſo knowne by reaſon, that bleſſedneſſe cannot be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then ſempiternall: Therefore it is well knowne, that Man is ordained to ſome euerlaſting perfection; which prooueth, that the Soule is Immortall The Minor doth Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> prooue, <hi>13. de Trin: ap 8. Si beata vita bearum d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erat, &amp;c. <hi>If ſo be the bleſſed ſife doe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the bleſſed man, hee being therevnto
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176301:37"/>either willing, or not willing, or neither of them: If not willing, how is it a bleſſed life; which is ſo in the Will, as it cannot be in the Power: If willing, how could that life be bleſſed, which he that had it, would not haue it verily and indeed: But if neither, Then ſuch a life, cannot in any wiſe be bleſſed, in ſuch a caſe, when he that it maketh bleſſed, is a ſtranger from the loue thereof.</hi>
                  </hi> This may in this wiſe be confirmed. Mans Soule is made to be partaker of bleſſedneſſe, to receiue it and enioy it. For this is certaine, truly proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the clamor of euery Appetite na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall: Therefore the Soule is made to receiue either eternall and perpetuall bleſſedneſſe, or elſe temporall. If the firſt, then the Soule is Immortall, and at the length ſhall be perpetually bleſſed. Now the ſecond cannot be; becauſe like as ſorrow commeth of thoſe thinges which happen vnto vs againſt our willes: euen ſo doth it of thoſe thinges that depart from vs againſt our willes. But bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if we ſhould be vnwilling vnto it, ſhould periſh, and become no bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at all: for how can we be bleſſed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176301:37"/>againſt our willes? And ſo bleſſedneſſe periſhing, our Soules, by a conſequent, ſhould haue in them ſelues a feare and griefe, and be alwaies ſorrowfull: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ſhould follow, that they ſhould be miſerable.</p>
               <p>Alſo, in euery well ordered ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, there are appointed rewards, to prouoke men to the doing of good; and puniſhmentes, to ſound the retreat from vices. But in the whole gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mankind, good and virtuous men are not ſufficiently rewarded; nor euill and naughtie men ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: yea, they cannot ſufficiently be rewarded, nor puniſhed; the one, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Gods Promiſe; the other, becauſe of his Iuſtice. Therefore there is another life, in the which ſhall be giuen to euery one according as his workes ſhall be. For no man could ſay, that the virtuous be rewarded with the pleaſures which Epicures enioy, and wherewith all they are delighted. Neither can it be ſaid, that the goods of Fortune (as they call them) can ſufficiently reward the virtuous; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that for the moſt part, we ſee the euill
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176301:38"/>men flow in riches, delightes, proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and all pleaſures that their heartes can deſire. On the contrarie part, the Virtuous doe often want theſe pleaſures and delightes, and are excruciated with many ſundry ſharpe ſhowers of Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. What then ſhall be giuen vnto the iuſt man, that hath abſtayned from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes, euen vnto the day of his death, and ſuſtayneth ſorrowes, pouertie, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, and tribulations?</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the worke of Virtue is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, incomparably then the goods of Fortune. And as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> witneſſeth, Honor and Fame, and chiefely of thoſe things which are outward goods: hence he ſayth, <hi>Maxime grauiter quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fert ſuo honore priuatus?</hi> (as wee vſe to ſay in our Engliſh,) <hi>Who is ſo woe begone, as firſt a man, and then none?</hi> But Honor is not a meete or worthy reward for Virtue: as the ſame <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth in the ſeauenth Booke of <hi>Ethickes. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtuti perfectae non vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dignus honor: <hi>Honor is no worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for perfect Virtue.</hi>
                  </hi> Neither is it auaileable to ſay, That the Virtuous are ſufficiently rewarded with eſſentiall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176301:38"/>goodneſſe, that inſeparably followeth a good Act. And that the Euill are puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the paine that inſeparably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth an euill Acte: which the Doctors call, <hi>Paenam derelictam, <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment left off;</hi>
                  </hi> and not Puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. Of which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, in his Booke of <hi>Confeſsions: <hi>Thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Lord, and ſo it is, that euerie ſinner is a puniſhment to himſelfe.</hi>
                  </hi> Of the which good, (as ſome ſay) the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſpeaketh in the 9. Booke of <hi>Ethickes,</hi> ſaying: <hi>That euery one that dieth for his Friende, doth purchaſe to himſelfe the greateſt good that may be.</hi> Moreouer, a leſſe delectation, for the moſt part, doth follow a greater operation; and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture none at all; as of the operations of Fortitude: Whereof it is that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſayth, in the third Booke of <hi>Ethickes, <hi>That in all Vertues, a man can not be occupied with delight.</hi>
                  </hi> Neither is it of force to ſay, that mans felicitie doth conſiſt in Sciences ſpeculatiue, or in the operations of Wiſedome, and in the knowledge of moſt high cauſes: And ſo by a conſequent, by ſuch like operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176301:39"/>of Wiſedome, a man ſhould ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently be rewarded in this life: As the Philoſopher and <hi>Auerrhois</hi> doe ſeeme to ſay. For the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentator vpon the firſt Booke of <hi>Phyſicks,</hi> ſayth: That it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to a man concerning his laſt perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be perfect according to the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſpeculatiue. And this Diſpoſition is vnto him his vtmoſt felicitie: And that heauenly life conſiſteth in this Science; becauſe that for Felicitie, a man ought to be good and perfect. But perfection, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Sciences ſpeculatiue, doth not make a man abſolutely neither good, nor the beſt: for many in ſuch thinges, may be perfect, which are vnhoneſt and vicious. A man vnhoneſt and full of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may be very ſkilfull and perfect in ſpeculatiue Sciences: for the diſpoſition to felicitie, is made better by virtues Morall, Heroicall, and Diuine. Whereof the Philoſopher ſayth in the 2. Booke of <hi>Ethicks, <hi>That it is a very meere beaſt lines to ſay, that we can be better, then by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues Heroicall &amp; Diuine.</hi>
                  </hi> Euen as <hi>Homer</hi> faigned, that <hi>Priamus</hi> ſayd of <hi>Hector; <hi>That becauſe he was ſo very good, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176301:39"/>not to be the ſonne of a mortall man, but of a God.</hi>
                  </hi> Wherefore if it be ſo, as they ſay; that Gods be made of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the notable excellencie of their Virtues; then ſuch like habite ſhall be oppoſite to beaſtlineſſe. And in the 10. Booke of <hi>Ethicks,</hi> the Philoſopher doth teach; <hi>That a man muſt ſo frame his workes and his life, that all be directed to this end, to witte, to get Felicitie.</hi> Vpon which, <hi>Auerrhois</hi> ſayth; <hi>If God haue a care of Men, as it is beleeued, and as it is meete he ſhould; he reioyceth of the better, and is delighted in thoſe that doe well; and it is meete and a worthy thing, that he doe well vnto, and reward thoſe that loue him more then others, or all thinges in the world, and honour them, and viſit them often, euen as it is the diſpoſition of one friend with another: therefore muſt wee doe our endeauour to become good.</hi> This is thus confirmed. Firſt, That then thoſe men that giue themſelues to Speculation, or doe practiſe and exerciſe themſelues in Speculatiue ſciences, howſoeuer they liued mortally and deſormedly, Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhould not be reputed bleſſed and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176301:40"/>happy, nor rewarded for their Merites. Secondly, If ſo be that God haue a care of Men, it is meete and moſt agreeable to reaſon, that his delight concerning men, ſhould be of that thing, which is the beſt in them, and which is moſt knowne vnto him, and moſt nigh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable vnto him; that is to ſay, which is moſt like vnto God; which is, to liue virtuouſly, according to the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: And alſo, that he doe well vnto, and reward thoſe that doe loue him: And beſtow benefites on thoſe, that for his ſake doe caſt away, contemne, and neglect worldly wealth, and delightfull pleaſures, and patiently ſuſtaine and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Aduerſitie, and willingly abide all Miſeries, euen vnto the day of their death. But he cannot ſufficiently reward them in this life: therefore the Soule is Immortall. The Minor is plaine; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe man is euen vnto death, vexed with Miſeries, Pouertie, and Aduerſities. The Maior is manifeſt, by the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, in the tenth Booke of <hi>Ethicks,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Seciendum intellectum autem operans, et hunc curans, &amp;c. <hi>Hee that worketh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:176301:40"/>to the vnderſtanding, and careth for it, doth ſeeme to be the beſt of all diſpoſed, and to loue God moſt: for if the Gods haue a certaine care of humaine thinges, as they ſeeme to haue; it ſhall then be moſt agreeable to reaſon, that the Gods them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues doe reioyce and delight in that thing which is the beſt and the nigheſt of kinne vnto them. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> Alſo it is thus confirmed: Becauſe, if the Soule ſhould be Mortall, and there ſhould be no life after this; then infinite euils ſhould remaine vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and good deedes ſhould not be rewarded: Which doth ſeeme deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to the equitie of Iuſtice, and to the comlineſſe and faireneſſe of humaine ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill gouernement. For what paine, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and miſerie, doth heere hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto thoſe euill men, who being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to delightes and pleaſures, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually euen vnto their death, heape euils vpon euils? Who (I ſay) ſhall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and take vengeance of thoſe Kings and Princes; by whoſe decrees, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, power, and authoritie, Common-weales are toſſed &amp; turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhaken and ſpoyled, by ſo many
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:176301:41"/>plagues, tormentes, vexations, violences, iniuries, and aduerſities? Who ſhall in this life be ſufficiently able to puniſh thoſe moſt grieuous ſinnes, that are done in ſecret, euill mindes, &amp; inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? What puniſhment then, I pray you, and miſerie, ſhall there be of theſe euils? Which if it be called the Priuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bleſſedneſſe, then ſhall all be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed: which ſeemeth to be dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie to the equitie of Iuſtice. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſeemeth moſt agreeable to reaſon, that there is a life of mans Soule after this; wherein euery one ſhall receiue worthily as he hath done in this life, whether it be good or euill.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, if mans Soule ſhould not liue after this life, in vaine then, and to no purpoſe ſhould we ſerue God heere; ſeeing that in this life, the worſhippe of God and Religion, is cruelly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, tormented, afflicted, and cruciated: and then is there after this life, no reward for it. In this poynt, it were better for the Soule, and more profitable by much, altogeather to denie God; and wholly to giue it ſelfe to euery vanitie &amp; pleaſure,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176301:41"/>then to liue holily and iuſtly, with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie miſeries, and to worſhip the Creator with due honouring and deuotion. Whereof the Apoſtle, in the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinths</hi> the fifteenth chapter ſaith: <hi>If in this life onely, we hope in Chriſt, then are wee of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> For if God hath no regard of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes and Worſhippers, where is his Power? ſeeing that neither in this life, (for this thing) he cannot be worſſe; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an other, better: ſeeing that after this, there is not another. But if he do not care, nor haue any regard, Where is his Wiſedome &amp; his Goodneſſe? Wherefore he ſhould ſeeme to be ignoraunt, not to know, or not to loue his louers and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers; if there be not another life after this: whereof the one deſtroyeth his Wiſedome, the other his Goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Out of theſe thinges aboue declared, is very eaſily enough diſprooued the raſh and erroneous opinion of <hi>Auerrhois,</hi> putting humaine felicitie, to conſiſt in the euery way and Actuall coniunction or copulation with the Vnderſtanding: And that Vnderſtanding, he would haue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176301:42"/>to be but one of all men, that all men haue but one vnderſtanding; as we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayd. For he ſayd, That man is then happie and ſufficiently rewarded, when that Vnderſtanding ſhall be euery way coupled vnto him. Which hee affirmed to be done, when a man ſhall actually haue all Vnderſtandinges ſpeculatiue. But this is vnpoſsible; becauſe that then there ſhould be togeather in acte, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely infinite things in the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we finde by experience in our ſelues, that the Attention to one thing, doth draw backe againe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Attention, about another thing. Seeing therefore the Vnderſtanding is of a finite vertue, it ſhall neuer be able to be coupled perfectly and actually to all ſpeculations. Who (I pray you) is found at all times, to be all one; the ſame in one thing, he was in another, ſkilfull alike in all thinges? Who ſo ſkilfull, that he can not be deceiued in any thing? Who is ſo perfect, that he is perfectly quieted in all thinges, and fully ſatisfied? Was not <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deceiued in many thinges, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176301:42"/>found ignoraunt in many thinges; as about the Eternitie of the World, and the Perpetuitie of generation and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and in very many other thinges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, he foully erred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conclusion">
               <head>The ſecond Concluſion.</head>
               <p>FAyth ſecluded and ſet apart, in the light of naturall Reaſon, it is more agreeable to Reaſon, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to affirme, that the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Soule is Immortall, then to ſay, that it is Mortall: Or that the opinion of thoſe Philoſophers that auouch, that the Soule is Immortall, is more reaſonable, and more probable: yea, Fayth being ſecluded and ſet aſide, then the oppoſite or contrary thereof. Firſt, it is very mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, according to the Philoſopher, that that is probable, which doth ſeeme to the moſt, euen chiefely to the wiſeſt. But very many of the Philoſophers, &amp; thoſe whom we ſee to be preferred aboue all others, of euery ſect and nation, in fame, glory, &amp; wiſedome, haue verily thought,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176301:43"/>the Soule to be Immortall. And but a few, and thoſe of the meaneſt of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, of no fame and reputation, haue ſaid, That it is Mortall; as hath been ſhewed before: therefore the Soule is Immortall.</p>
               <p>Hereof the Philoſopher ſayth, in the ninth Booke of <hi>Ethicks,</hi> that, <hi>Opinionibus ſapientum oportet acquieſcere, habent enim fidem quandam:</hi> 1. <hi>Wee ought for to reſt and ſtay our ſelues in the Opinions of Wiſemen: for they haue a certaine Fayth.</hi> Whereof he alſo ſayth: <hi>That the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Wiſemen doe ſound togeather, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo that Opinion is more reaſonable and probable, whereunto there are more effectuall perſwaſions, or more dialecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reaſons. But for this Opinion, That the Soule is Immortall, there are more effectuall perſwaſions, and more Topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reaſons, then for the contrarie opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Yea for that part, the reaſons are moſt ſlender: neither haue they ſcarſely any ſhadow of probabilitie; for all the reaſons wherewith they goe about to impugne the Immortalitie of the Soule, are founded in errour, or on a falſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176301:43"/>ground; as are theſe wherevnto all (for the moſt part) doe leane. If the Soule ſhould be Immortall, it ſhould follow, that all the Soules ſhould be perpetually idle and depriued of their proper act. But this Reaſon is grounded on two thinges: whereof both are falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous. The firſt is, that the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corrupted, cannot be repayred and brought againe to the ſame forme and maner that it was before. The ſecond is, That the Soule cannot vnderſtand but in the Body, &amp; by the meanes of the Body: of which thinges at this preſent, it is not needfull to ſpeake. Alſo, Reaſons dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecticall, how effectuall or forceable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they ſhall be; or multiplied out of the nature of them, or from the Empire or Godly affection of the Will, cannot cauſe but an opinion or aſſent, with a feare of the oppoſite. From the ſame feate, are Reaſons bred with the empire of the Will, &amp; the godly Affection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to cauſe a greater aſſent in the kind of opinion: yea verily, ſometimes Fayth, or a firme Aſſent without feare of the oppoſite; whereof the Philoſopher ſaith,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176301:44"/>in the ſeauenth Booke of <hi>Ethicks,</hi> that, <hi>Aligui ita firmiter harent his de quibus habent opinionem, ſicut alij his quibus habent ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam:</hi> 1. <hi>Some doe ſo firmely cleaue to the thinges whereof they haue opinion, as others doe to thoſe thinges whereof they haue full knowledge or ſkill.</hi> And this proceedes of the empire and godly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Will: Whereof the Text thus lyeth: <hi>Some that doe hold Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doe not doubt, but eſteeme or thinke that they doe ſurely know that whereof they hold opinion, and doe nothing leſſe belieue thoſe that are of opinion, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thoſe that know.</hi> But euery one well diſpoſed, is inclined, <hi>Ad eſſe, et non ad non eſſe. <hi>To bee, and not to not bee;</hi>
                  </hi> to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue, not negatiue; and is affected to alwayes to bee, if it be poſsible: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others being like, euery one well diſpoſed is borne to haue a greater Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, yea a firmer and a ſurer, that the Soule is Immortall, then of the oppoſite thereof.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is more agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and more probable in the light of naturall reaſon to ſuppoſe, or to thinke,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176301:44"/>that the Soule is Immortall, then the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite thereof. Whereof our <hi>Cicero</hi> thought it more ſaf &amp; ſecure, to erre with thoſe Philoſophers that hold that the Soule is Immortal, then with thoſe meane and baſe accounted on Philoſophers, that doe affirme and hold of opinion, that the Soule is Mortall.</p>
               <p>If the Soule be Mortall, then they that hold it to be Immortal, do not therby get any detriment, loſſe, hinderance, or euill: neither can they be blamed in an other life, nor noted of ignorance. If it be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, then they that hold it to be Mortall, are worthy in an other life, to be reprehended &amp; laughed to ſcorne. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is more agreeable to reaſon in the light of naturall reaſon, to ſay, that the Soule is Immortall, then to ſay, that it is Mortall. For ſo ſaith <hi>Cicero: Quod ſi in hoc erro quod animos hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immortales eſſe, lebenter erro. Nec mihi hunc errorem quo delector dum viuo extorqueri volo. Sin mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vt quidam minuti Philoſophi cenſent, nihil ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntiam. Non vereor ne hunc errorem meum Philoſophi mortui irrideant: <hi>If ſo be I doe erre in this, that I beleeued the Soules to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176301:45"/>be Immortall, I doe willingly erre: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while I liue, will I be wreſted away from this error wherein I am delighted: But when I am dead, as certaine meane Philoſophers doe thinke, I ſhall feele no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; I doe not feare, leaſt the dead Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſhould ſcorne this my errour.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the foreſayd Philoſophers, of whom wee haue ſpoken aboue, not ouercome by euident reaſons and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, but fully ſetled and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the foreſaid perſwaſions, and all other reaſons probable; which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities ſake I omit, haue concluded; That the Soule is Immortall. For the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in following Naturall reaſon, haue written and taught thoſe thinges, which they haue not prooued euidently, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by demonſtratiue reaſon: but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſiuely and dilectically. They alſo ſuppoſed, thought, and concluded, many thinges without any great proofe, by mingling and conforming themſelues to the opinions of the common people, and the ſentences of the Philoſophers that were before them. Whereof the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher ſaith, <hi>Secundo de caelo, cap. <hi>Of two
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176301:45"/>hard Queſtions</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>it is to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which thing we ſhould ſay, is the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing.</hi> Reputing Promptitude to be imputed a poynt of ſhamefaſtneſſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then of bouldneſſe. If any do ſtand on Philoſophies part, and doth loue few ſufficiencies of that thing whereof we haue very great doubtinges, whence few ſufficiencies &amp; perſwaſions vſually haue ſufficed Philoſophers, where they were not able to attaine to greater thinges; neither did they contradict the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Philoſophie, or the opinions of their predeceſſours; wherein Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers on all ſides reſted, becauſe of their probable probations, and ſometime for the aſſertions of their formors; becauſe of neceſſarie reaſon.</p>
               <p>And in the ſame Chapter, <hi>De alijs aſtris, dicunt Aegiptij et Babilonicj, &amp;c. <hi>Of other Starres, doe ſpeake the</hi>
                  </hi> Aegiptians <hi>and</hi> Babilonians, <hi>from whom wee haue many thinges that wee doe beleeue of euery our of thoſe Starres: But in the ſciences of Aſtrologie and Aſtronomie, haue flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the ſonnes of</hi> Seth, Noe, Abraham, Salomon, <hi>and the holy Fathers; which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176301:46"/>haue taught Philoſophers, of ſecrets Celeſtiall and Diuine: vnto the which they could not haue attained by humaine ſtrength and naturall reaſon.</hi> But <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in the firſt Booke of the <hi>Antiquities of the Iewes,</hi> ſayth: That <hi>Seth,</hi> when he came to that age, that could diſcerne good thinges, gaue him ſelfe to the ſtudie of Virtue; and when he was become an excellent man, he left his Sonnes to be followers of himſelfe; they all being the Sonnes of a good Father, tarryed in the ſame Land, liuing moſt happily without any vexation; and firſt found out the diſcipline and learning of thinges Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall, and the trimneſſe of them. And leaſt they ſhould ſlide away from men, and vtterly periſh, ſeeing they had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of <hi>Adam,</hi> that there ſhould be one extermination of all thinges by Fire, and an other by the power and force of Water; they made two Pillars, one of Braſſe, and an other of Stone, and wrote therein what they had found out of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall thinges, that they might leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, the knowledge of Celeſtiall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:176301:46"/>
               <p>And in the Secrets of Secrets, it is ſaid; That the glorious GOD, hath ordained the meane and remedie to temper Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and preſerue Health; and how to get many other thinges. And hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it to Prophets and Holy men, and others, whom he fore-choſe and illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſpirit of his Wiſedome. Of theſe, the men that followed, had the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and originall of Philoſophie; <hi>Aegiptians, Greekes, Latines:</hi> from whom the latter haue drawne and written the principles of Artes and Sciences. And (ſayth he to <hi>Alexander,</hi>) it is meete and worthy, that he know noble Phiſicke, which is ſayd to be a glory ineſtimable, and is called, The Treaſure of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. I truely haue neuer truely or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly enough learned it: neither doe I know who it was that inuented it. Some affirme, that <hi>Adam</hi> was the inuentor thereof. Some ſay that it was <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes</hi> the Phiſition <hi>Hirſos</hi> and <hi>Domaſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Mati<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dos hebrewes,</hi> and <hi>Dioris,</hi> and <hi>Carus,</hi> glorious Philoſophers. Many ſay, that <hi>Henooh</hi> by a viſion knew this ſecret: whom many will haue to be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176301:47"/>that great <hi>Hermogenes</hi> whom the <hi>Greekes</hi> do prayſe, and to him commend all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſecret &amp; celeſtiall. Wherefore in the Prologue of the Books of <hi>Hermes Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Triplex Triſmegiſtus,</hi> it is thus ſayd: We read in old Hiſtories of Diuines, that there were Three Philoſophers: whereof the firſt was <hi>Henoch,</hi> who is alſo called <hi>Hermes,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>Noe;</hi> who was called <hi>Hermes:</hi> for he (as <hi>Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muzar</hi> witneſſeth) was a great Prophet, and firſt builded &amp; peopled <hi>Babilon</hi> after the Flood, and inſtructed them in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and learning. His ſonne <hi>Sem</hi> alſo taught the <hi>Babilonians</hi> or <hi>Caldeans,</hi> and deliuered vnto them the ſcience of the Starres. The third, was called <hi>Hermes Mercurius Triplex,</hi> becauſe he was a King, a Philoſopher, &amp; a Prophet: hee flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed after the Flood, &amp; with great equitie gouerned the Kingdome of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and clearely brightened Aſtronomie. And in the Booke of the Death of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> it is ſaid; that, After <hi>Noe,</hi> was <hi>Abraham</hi> borne, who being wiſer then all, did thorowly come to the great degree of Philoſophie: for he knew that <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> had a firſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176301:47"/>moouer, and therefore he followed not the way of his Father, neither of his Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, that worſhipped Idols: But (as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> witneſſeth in his Booke of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities of the Iewes,</hi>) hee preuayled to change &amp; innouate that opinion, which then all had of God: for hee firſt preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to pronounce God, one God to be the only Creator of all things: for he, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hiſtories of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> taught the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> Arithmeticke, and alſo Aſtronomie. Theſe, and many other ſecrets, were planted in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> which are knowne to haue come to the <hi>Greekes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the doctrines therefore of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, illuminated from Heauen, the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers that came after, being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as it were ſtrengthned by the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Prophets, haue conſcribed many glorious Sciences, which they could not attaine vnto by the force of mans witte. Did not <hi>Plato</hi> goe into <hi>Aegipt</hi> to learne Aſtrologie? And there (as it is thought of all for the moſt part) hee learned what great thinges ſoeuer were there had and taught. And chiefely theſe things which are knowne to be agreeing to our Fayth.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176301:48"/>Not that <hi>Hieremias,</hi> as ſome ſuppoſe, ſaw or read the Tranſlation of the Seauentie: For <hi>Plato</hi> was borne almoſt an hundred yeares, from the time that <hi>Jeremie</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied: Who ſeeing that he liued foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares and one; from the yeare of his death, to the tranſlation of the ſeauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Interpreaters, are found threeſcore yeares: Wherefore <hi>Ieremie</hi> could neither ſee nor read the Tranſlation of the holy Scriptures, ſeeing hee was dead ſo long before they were tranſlated into the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue. But becauſe he was a man of a very ſharpe witte, as the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> are, hee ſo did learne the foreſayd holy Scriptures by an Interpreater; as thoſe thinges in <hi>Timaeo,</hi> which hee there wrote of the trueth of our Religion, doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Out of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> they ſay, that <hi>Plato</hi> came into <hi>Italie,</hi> and there learned all the doctrine of <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> But of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of mens Soules, hee did not onely perceiue and know the ſame that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> did, but alſo brought and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereunto reaſons, which they afore him (in a maner) did not. Whoſe Booke of the <hi>Immortalitie of the Soule;</hi> a worke
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176301:48"/>moſt elegant, <hi>Cato</hi> the later (before hee flew himſelfe) did twiſe read ouer, as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> reporteth: which when hee had read, he ſo departed this life, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced that he was borne to the end to die; ſo great ſurely was the force and power of this Booke, to perſwade the Immortalitie of mens mindes, that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebrotus</hi> a certaine man of <hi>Ambrochia,</hi> when no aduerſitie would befall him to end his life, he got him vp vpon a very high Wall, and caſt himſelfe into the Sea, after that he had read the foreſayd Booke of <hi>Plato;</hi> of whom Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his firſt Booke, <hi>De ciuitate Dej,</hi> and the 22. chapter, writeth thus. <hi>Therebrotus libro Platonis vbi de immortalitate animae diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit ſe praecipitem dedit e muro, vt ſic ab iſta vita migraret ad eandem quam credidit mehorem.</hi> 1. Therebrotus, <hi>when he had read ouer the Booke of</hi> Plato, <hi>where he hath diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Immortalitie of the Soule, caſt himſelfe downe headlong from a Wall, that ſo he might flit away from this life, vnto that ſame which he beleeued to be better.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:176301:49"/>
               <head>The third Concluſion.</head>
               <p>BY vndoubted Fayth and Beliefe, it is to be holden, that the Soule of euery man is Immortall: And firſt, it is manifeſt by the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, in the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat. 10. verſ. 28.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. Feare ye not them which kill the Body, but are not able to kill the Soule: but rather feare him which is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both Body and Soule in Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat. ca. 18. v. 9.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. It is better for thee to enter into Life halt, then hauing two feete, to be caſt into Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mar. 9.43.44.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="43">43. Wherefore, if thy Hand cauſe thee to offende, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter into Life maimed, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing two Handes, to goe into Hell, into Fire that neuer ſhalbe quenched.</p>
               <p n="44">44. Where the Worme dieth not, and the Fire neuer goeth out. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat. 25.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="31">31. When the Sonne of man commeth
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:176301:49"/>in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him: then ſhall he ſit vpon the Throne of his glorie.</p>
               <p n="32">32. And before him ſhalbe gathered all Nations; and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as the Shepheard ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth the Sheepe from the Goates.</p>
               <p n="33">33. And he ſhall ſet the Sheepe on his right hand, and the Goates on his left.</p>
               <p n="34">34. Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand: Come ye bleſſed chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of my Father, inherite the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world.</p>
               <p n="41">41. Then ſhall he ſay to them on his left hand: Depart from me yee curſſed, into euerlaſting Fire, which is prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>My Sheepe heare my voyce, &amp; I giue vnto them eternall life.</p>
               <p>¶ Of theſe Places, I doe conclude, that the Soule is Immortall: becauſe it liueth eternally, or is puniſhed euerlaſtingly.</p>
               <p>In the Booke of Wiſedome, cap. 3.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Soules of the Righteous, are in the hand of God: and no torment ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176301:50"/>touch them.</item>
                  <item>2 In the ſight of the Vnwiſe, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to die: and their end was thought grieuous.</item>
                  <item>3. And their departing from vs, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; but they are in peace.</item>
                  <item>4. And though they ſuffer paine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men: yet is their hope full of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</item>
                  <item>5. They are puniſhed in few thinges, yet in many thinges ſhall they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded: for God prooueth them, and findeth them meete for him.</item>
                  <item>6. He tryeth them as Gould in the furnace, and receiueth them as a perfect fruit offring.</item>
                  <item>7. And in the time of their viſion, they ſhall ſhine, and run through as the ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles among the ſtubble.</item>
                  <item>8. They ſhall iudge the nations, and haue Dominion ouer the people, and their Lord ſhall raigne for euer.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtos. 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe man ſhall goe to the houſe of his eternity. Alſo in the laſt iudgement, euery man that is predeſtinate to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall riſe againe to life euerlaſting,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176301:50"/>with the ſame Bodyes they had heere, according to that ſaying of <hi>Job.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job. 19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25. I am ſure that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and that I ſhall riſe againe out of the earth at the laſt day.</p>
               <p n="26">26. And though after my ſkinne, Wormes deſtroy this Body: yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Whom I my ſelfe ſhall ſee; yea, my ſelfe ſhall behold, and none other for me.</p>
               <p>So that hereby it is very manifeſt and plaine, that all the Soules of men, ſhall euery one of them take againe their owne proper Bodyes being become Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, or brought vnto the ſtate of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of the good and bleſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1. Theſsal. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. If we beleeue that Ieſus is dead, and is riſen: euen ſo them that ſleepe in Ieſus, will God bring with him.</p>
               <p n="16">16. For the Lord himſelfe ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from Heauen with a ſhoute, and with the voyce of the Archangell, and with the Troumpe of God: and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:176301:51"/>
               <p n="17">17. Then ſhall we which liue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, be caught vp with them alſo, in the Cloudes, to meete the Lord in the Aire: and ſo ſhall wee euer be with the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom. 6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If wee be dead with Chriſt to the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of his death, euen ſo ſhall we be to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If we be dead with Chriſt, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that we alſo ſhall liue with him.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Knowing that Chriſt, being rayſed from the death, dieth no more; death hath no more power ouer him.</p>
               <p>¶ <hi>Of all good and bad, is plaine in the Epiſtle to the Corinthians. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51. Wee ſhall not all ſleepe; but wee ſhalbe all changed.</p>
               <p n="52">52. In moment of time, by the laſt Trumpet: for the Trumpet ſhall blow, and the dead ſhall be rayſed vp incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</p>
               <p n="53">53. For this corruptible, muſt put on incorruption: and this mortall, muſt put on immortalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:176301:51"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>OF theſe Authorities and Reaſons, there may in the minde of euery faythfull man, that vndoubtedly beleeueth the holy Scriptures, be bred a ſufficient Fayth of the Immortalitie of the Soule, ſufficient (I ſay) to ſaluation: yea, it doth not ſeeme poſsible, that thoſe that are inſtructed in the foreſayd Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhould doubt of the Immortalitie of the Soule: For it doth not ſeeme natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to be poſsible, that ſome one eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Aſſent, that the Antecedent can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be true, without the Conſequent; and vndoubtedly Aſſent to the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but the muſt vndoubtedly Aſſent to the Conſequent, which he doth euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know to be concluded and deducted out of the Antecedent. But the Reaſons Topicall, or Perſwaſions Probable, which we haue before ſet downe, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the ſecond part of the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; although (as it is ſayd) it be not of their nature, to breed nothing elſe but an Opinion or Aſſent with feare of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176301:52"/>Oppoſite; (for Opinion is the accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one part of the Contradiction, with feare of the other:) yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, out of the empire of the Will, they may breed a firme and ſure Aſſent, of the Immortalitie of the Soule, aboue Opinion, and beneath Science; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſame euidence, and not adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie.</p>
               <p>From hence may ſuch perſwaſions or reaſons be able manifoldly and ſundry wayes, to profite and auayle the fayth of the faythfull, for they helpe our Fayth; for by them, in the vnfaythfull, is begun the Fayth of the Immortalitie of the Soule. By them, is the ſame Fayth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rued and ſtrengthned againſt the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and Heretickes: By the ſame, is it ſuſlayned and defended: thereby, are the ſimple (at the length) throughly mooued and prouoked to true Fayth. Wherefore <hi>Peter</hi> commaundeth, To be readie prepared to render to euery one that aſketh, a reaſon of the Fayth that is in vs. But the faythfull man, hauing ſuch like reaſons and perſwaſions, doth not leane to the firſt trueth and concluſion
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176301:52"/>of Fayth, or that the Soule is Immortall principally for thoſe ſame reaſons, but rather doth aſſent to them, and vſeth them, which doe conſent to the firſt trueth, that it is well: as the Lord ſayth by the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> that worſhipped in the Mount: By whom are figured and ſignified the true beleeuers; who ſeeing <hi>JESVS</hi> by Fayth, are called <hi>Samaritanes.</hi> This is to humaine reaſon; <hi>Now we doe not beleeue becauſe of thy ſaying, but becauſe wee our ſelues haue ſeene and heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe thinges, it moſt plainely and moſt euidently appeareth, how great thankes are to be giuen vnto the moſt high GOD, and Father of Mercies, and to our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath moſt certainely aſſured, and fully perſwaded his Faythfull ones, in theſe things, where vnto the moſt Wittie, &amp; the beſt Learned men that euer were in all the World, could not, by the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, preuaile ſufficiently to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: to witte, of the Laſt end of the reaſonable Creature, of the Reſurrection of the Dead, of the Immortalitie of the reaſonable Soule, and of the perpetuall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:176301:53"/>Eternitic of the ſame. And this, hath that Almighty Lord &amp; moſt merciful Father, ſo done in ſuch ſort; that now it is not lawfull for vs, neither is there any neede, to doubt in theſe thinges, or to flow out, or run any where elſe to ſeeke for props or ſtayes of our Fayth in theſe matters. Neither is it needfull from hence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; after this time of ſo great Grace reuealed to ſeeke, or put to new reaſons or probable perſwaſions: becauſe wee are moſt firmely holden, without feare of the oppoſite: or without any Ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie, to beleeue that the Good &amp; iuſt doe gloriouſly liue eternally with Chriſt. And that the Euill are tormented perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually with the Diuell &amp; his Angels: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the fifth of <hi>Iohn. And they that haue done euill, ſhall come foorth vnto the reſurrection of Iudgement: and they that haue done good, to the reſurrection of Life;</hi> Which God ſhall giue to them, which neuer change their Fayth from him. Which God graunt vnto vs, who is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:176301:53"/>
            <head>Of the Immortalitie of the Soule, out of <hi>Palingenius in Capricorne.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>BEcauſe thou ſhalt beleeue, I will declare to thee,</l>
            <l>By reaſon good, the ſtate of Soule, Immortall for to bee.</l>
            <l>For if that God in better thinges, doth Cunning ſtill expreſſe,</l>
            <l>As Wiſdome telles, and as the good, and virtuous muſt confeſſe:</l>
            <l>Then doubtleſſe muſt we iudge he gaue, the Soules no time to die,</l>
            <l>Since better farre it is for them to liue continually.</l>
            <l>Then with the fleſh to be extinct, and feele a full decay:</l>
            <l>Which thus I prooue. If death do take from vs the Soule away,</l>
            <l>If that we haue no other life, but in this body heere:</l>
            <l>Then God may be accounpted ill, and ſhall vniuſt appeare.</l>
            <l>For thouſands euerie day wee ſee, that floriſh proſperouſly,</l>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:176301:54"/>
            <l>In Ritches, Subſtance and Renounce, in Raignes and Empires hie.</l>
            <l>Yet idle Lubbers, naught, vnlearnd, that ſinne at libertie,</l>
            <l>And run the race of all their life in great proſperitie.</l>
            <l>On th'other ſide we may behold, the iuſt oppreſt to bee:</l>
            <l>With ſpightfull chaunce, a wretched life and pitious pouertie:</l>
            <l>Thus either God vnrighteous is, that doth this thing permit:</l>
            <l>Or after death, hath euery man, as he deſerueth fit:</l>
            <l>Or elſe he doth diſdaine the deedes, of mortall men to know,</l>
            <l>Beſides, what gratious minde in God, what goodnes doth he ſhow?</l>
            <l>If this be all that he doth giue, a life ſo ſhort and vaine,</l>
            <l>That ſwiftly runneth to an end, and doth no time remaine:</l>
            <l>The halfe whereof is ſpent in ſleepe, the reſt in griefe and toyle?</l>
            <l>And dangers great as faſt doth fleete, as Riuers ſwift in ſoyle.</l>
            <l>Therefore goe to, o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wretched men,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176301:54"/>build gorgious Churches hie,</l>
            <l>And let with coſtly Offrings great, your Altars peſtred lie.</l>
            <l>Set vp your ioy full branch of Bayes, your ſacred doores about:</l>
            <l>With pompe of proud Proceſsion paſſe, let Hymnes be ratled out.</l>
            <l>Spend Frankincenſe, and let the noſe of God be ſtretched wide;</l>
            <l>With pleaſant ſmoke doe this, and adde more honour much beſide.</l>
            <l>That he preſerue your goodly life, wherein doth you torment,</l>
            <l>Somtime great cold, and ſomtime heate, now plague, now famiſhment.</l>
            <l>Now bloody warre, now ſickneſſe great or Chance to ſorrow at:</l>
            <l>Sometime the buſie Flie, ſometime the ſtinging Gnat,</l>
            <l>The Chynch and Flea; reioyce I ſay, that heere you lead your life,</l>
            <l>With thouſand painefull labours great, in trauaile, toyle, and ſtrife.</l>
            <l>And after, in a litle ſpace, in paine you drop away:</l>
            <l>And lumpiſh lie in loath ſome Vault, to Wormes a gratefull prey.</l>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:176301:55"/>
            <l>O worthy life, O goodly gift: Man in this world is bred,</l>
            <l>Among the brutiſh Beaſtes and fooles, and knaues, his life is led,</l>
            <l>Where Stormes, and flakie Snows, &amp; Ice, and Durt, and Duſt, and Night.</l>
            <l>And harmfull aire, and clowds, &amp; miſtes, and windes, with helliſh fight,</l>
            <l>And griefe and wayling raignes: where death beſide, doth worke his feat.</l>
            <l>Is this our goodly Countrie heere? Is this our happy ſeate,</l>
            <l>For which we owe ſuch ſeruice heere, vnto the Gods aboue:</l>
            <l>For which it ſeemeth meete with vowes the heauenly Saintes to moone?</l>
            <l>And if none other life we haue, then this of body vaine:</l>
            <l>So frayle and full of filthineſſe, when Death hath Carcaſſe ſlaine.</l>
            <l>I ſee not why ſuch Prayſes ſhould, of God reſound in Ayre:</l>
            <l>For why we ſhould ſuch honour giue, to him in Temples fayre;</l>
            <l>That hath vs wretches framed heere, in this ſo wretched ſoyle:</l>
            <l>That ſhall for euermore decay,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176301:55"/>after ſo great a toyle.</l>
            <l>Wherfore leaſt God ſhould ſeeme vniuſt and full of cruelneſſe,</l>
            <l>Shall well deſeruing counted be, we muſt of force confeſſe,</l>
            <l>That Death doth not deſtroy the Soule, but that it alwayes is,</l>
            <l>None otherwiſe then Spirit in Ayre, or Saintes in heauens bliſſe:</l>
            <l>Both voyde of body, ſleepe, and meate. And more, we muſt confeſſe,</l>
            <l>That after death, they liue in paines, or elſe in bleſſedneſſe:</l>
            <l>But let this reaſon thee ſuffice, for if thou doe it ſhow</l>
            <l>Vnto the wicked kind, they laugh; no light the blind doth know.</l>
            <l>But thou, beleeue for euermore, and know aſſuredly.</l>
            <l>(For ground of ſauing health it is) that Soules doe neuer die.</l>
            <l>Exempted from the Siſters power, and fatall Deſtinie.</l>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Palingenius in Libra.</head>
               <l>We need not doubt, but Soule proceedes and doth from <hi>loue</hi> deſcend,</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:176301:56"/>
               <l>And neuer dies: whom he permits, the World to comprehend.</l>
               <l>What if ſo be, the <hi>Atomies,</hi> which ſome Wiſe men do fayne,</l>
               <l>The Soule is rather thought to bee, than body to maintaine.</l>
               <l>All Bodyes be of quantitie, and may deuided be:</l>
               <l>But Soule is indiuiſible, and of no groſſe degree.</l>
               <l>And as a Centre doth ſhe ſeeme, where many Lines doe meete:</l>
               <l>Which Senſes all to her conuey, as Floods to Seas, doe fleete.</l>
               <l>Wherefore I maruaile much at ſuch, as thinke a like decay:</l>
               <l>And iudge the Soule no more to bee, when Body fades away.</l>
               <l>For if ſo be it might be prooude, yet ſhould it not be ſayd;</l>
               <l>Nor Publiſht to the common ſort, nor euery way diſplayd.</l>
               <l>For many wicked men, and ill there are, which if they thought,</l>
               <l>Their Soules as nothing ſhall remaine, when corps to graue is brought:</l>
               <l>Nor that it feeles, or ſuffers ought,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176301:56"/>when it goeth hence away,</l>
               <l>And that no puniſhment remaines, for prancks that here they play:</l>
               <l>A thouſand miſchifes would they doe, (take feare from them among)</l>
               <l>And fall to euery vilonie, confounding right with wrong.</l>
               <l>Beſides, a number now that thinke in bleſſed ſtate to bee,</l>
               <l>When death hath them deſtroyd, &amp; hope the face of God to ſee:</l>
               <l>And euermore with him to ioy, and therefore virtuouſly</l>
               <l>Doe ſeeke to paſſe their preſent life, with godly modeſlie.</l>
               <l>If they ſhall ſee that after death, doe no rewardes remaine:</l>
               <l>Amaſed all, their virtuous workes, ſhall ceaſe and periſh plaine.</l>
               <l>So many ſtately Temples trimde, ſo many Altars hie,</l>
               <l>With Gold and Marble garniſhed, and decked ſumptuouſly.</l>
               <l>Beſide Religion, Godly zeale, Honour and worſhipping</l>
               <l>Of God, ſhall come to nought, if after death remaine nothing,</l>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:176301:57"/>
               <l>That men may hope for, if the Soule as Winde doth paſſe away.</l>
               <l>Of wild and franticke common ſort, Religion muſt be ſtay,</l>
               <l>And feare of ſmart: for miſchiuous, and full of fraud their braine,</l>
               <l>Is alwayes ſeene, nor of themſelues, they well doe meane, or plaine.</l>
               <l>The common ſort doe Virtue loath, and euermore her hate.</l>
               <l>Religion is the comlineſſe, and glorie of our ſtate.</l>
               <l>Which makes the Gods to fauour vs, which we winne Heauen by.</l>
               <l>No wiſe nor good man therefore dare, attempt her openly,</l>
               <l>To teach that Soule ſhal come to nought and ſo corrupt the mindes,</l>
               <l>Of rude vnſkilfull common ſort, that wauer like the windes.</l>
               <l>Now muſt we teach by reaſon good, that Soules ſhall neuer die;</l>
               <l>But free from ſting, or dart of death, doe liue eternally.</l>
               <l>Which euery Chriſtian man doth hold, and Greſhop eater Iew,</l>
               <l>(Who our foreſkins abhorres) beleeues:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176301:57"/>which God that all thinges knew,</l>
               <l>Would not haue made, if he had thought they had been needleſſe, ſure:</l>
               <l>And Nations all beſides, do thinke that Soules ſhall aye endure.</l>
               <l>For firſt the thing reſembling moſt, the mightieſt Lord of all:</l>
               <l>Of longer laſting life we count, and perfecter muſt call.</l>
               <l>For that which doth not long endure, but ſhortly doth decay,</l>
               <l>That it ſhould be vnperfecter, who is that will ſay nay?</l>
               <l>And therefore do celeſtiall thinges, a greater while endure:</l>
               <l>Becauſe they are more perfecter, and more Diuine and pure.</l>
               <l>But thinges that nearer are the earth, and fartheſt off from ſkies,</l>
               <l>Vnperfect ſince they are; do fade, and ſooneſt euer dyes.</l>
               <l>Shall then our Soule, ſith life in it and knowledge doth appeare,</l>
               <l>Moſt like vnto the ſtate Diuine, be cloſde and ſhut vp heere</l>
               <l>With Body for to end? Nor ſhall it heere haue longer place,</l>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:176301:58"/>
               <l>Then fading fleſh? Or ſhall it liue no more, nor larger ſpace?</l>
               <l>Beſides, that Soules cannot decay, this Reaſon witneſſe ſhall:</l>
               <l>Becauſe it is of ſingle ſtate, and voyde of matter all.</l>
               <l>Adde this, that when the Body fades, the force of Minde doth grow</l>
               <l>As weake and aged Fathers old doe more good Counſell know,</l>
               <l>Then youthful blouds of younger years and often he lacks wit</l>
               <l>That doth excell in ſtrength and force, for rare doth God permit</l>
               <l>Both ſtrength and wit to any one. Wherefore, if force brought low,</l>
               <l>By ſpace and courſe of many yeares, the Minde doth ſtronger grow.</l>
               <l>Of Body doth it not depend, but of it ſelfe conſiſt</l>
               <l>Another thing: and after Graue doth liue, and death reſiſt.</l>
               <l>Doth not beſide when foote doth ake, the Minde iudge thereof plaine?</l>
               <l>It is no doubt. But how can griefe, to towre of Minde attaine?</l>
               <l>Doth it aſcend from loweſt partes
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176301:58"/>as Smoke doth vpward flie?</l>
               <l>No: for many partes, not foote alone, (if ſo) ſhould ake thereby.</l>
               <l>Nor of the foote, but of the part that neareſt is to Minde</l>
               <l>The ake ſhould grieue. This ſhewes that Soule is not of Bodyes kind;</l>
               <l>And is ſo free from death, ſince it in diſtance needes no meane,</l>
               <l>Adde this, when we would call to minde the thing forgotten cleane;</l>
               <l>Or elſe deuiſe ſome worthy fetch, from Minde, the Senſes all,</l>
               <l>It then behoues to gather vp, whereby doth often fall,</l>
               <l>That many better for to muſe, doe ſhut vp cloſe their eyes:</l>
               <l>Or elſe forſaking companie, ſome ſecret place deuiſe.</l>
               <l>Or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the night with darkſome cloude the earth doth ouer ſpread;</l>
               <l>And creatures all with heauie ſleepe, do take their reſt in bed:</l>
               <l>They ſtill do watch, and ſilent all vpon their beds doe reſt;</l>
               <l>And light put out, in darkneſſe whet their Minde with Body preſt.</l>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:176301:59"/>
               <l>For Senſes doe the Minde diſturbe, Affections it deſtroyes,</l>
               <l>Amazing it with Dulneſſe great, and Blindneſſe it annoyes:</l>
               <l>None otherwiſe then Cloudes do hide, the Sunne that clearely ſhines;</l>
               <l>If therefore, when it doth remaine within his owne confines,</l>
               <l>And flying farre from Senſes all, and cares that Body bringes:</l>
               <l>It wiſer be, then ſhall it know, and vnderſtand all thinges,</l>
               <l>In better ſort, when it is free, and from the fleſh doth flie;</l>
               <l>More perfect of it ſelfe it is, and liues continually.</l>
               <l>Againe, ſith Man as Meane conſiſtes, the Saintes and Beaſtes betwixt:</l>
               <l>Some part with each, he common holds with Beaſt his Body mixt.</l>
               <l>And with the Saintes his Minde agrees; one of theſe partes doth die:</l>
               <l>Of th'other, death can haue no power, but liues continually.</l>
               <l>Death therefore takes not all away: for why? his deadly dartes,</l>
               <l>Doe neuer harme the Soule a whit,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176301:59"/>when it from Body partes.</l>
               <l>And more then this, I haue to ſay, if nothing doe remaine</l>
               <l>Of vs, when Carcaſſe lyes in Tombe, God ſhall be called plaine</l>
               <l>Vniuſt, and one that fauour ſhewes to ſuch as naughtie liue.</l>
               <l>For ſuch, for tearme of all their life, no Sorrowes do them grieue:</l>
               <l>No Ritches lacke, nor Pleaſures great, but happily reioyce;</l>
               <l>Exalted with Promotions hie, and with the Commons voyce.</l>
               <l>On th'other ſide, the Virtuous men, a thouſand Griefes moleſt,</l>
               <l>now ſore diſeaſd, now plagu'd with need In fine, alwayes oppreſt.</l>
               <l>Therefore the Soule liues after graue, and feeles deſerued paynes:</l>
               <l>And if it haue done iuſtly heere, a Crowne of Glorie gaines.</l>
               <l>By theſe, and many other wayes, I could declare, no doubt,</l>
               <l>That Soule of man doth neuer die, and Body liues without.</l>
               <l>But thi's enough time bids me end. Not ignorant am I;</l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:176301:60"/>
               <l>That ſome, the ſoule (although vnapt) doe tearme an Harmonie.</l>
               <l>And as of ſundry voyces mou'd, proceedes a melodie:</l>
               <l>Of ſundry Compounds Medcine made, which heale with ſoueraigntie.</l>
               <l>So of the ioyned Elements, by certaine meane and way,</l>
               <l>Created of the Heauens eke the Soule to be, ſome ſay;</l>
               <l>A part whereof in Body dwels, and part abroad doth lie:</l>
               <l>As ſight doth ſpring of outward light, and virtue of the eye.</l>
               <l>But this opinion is not true; for if it ſhould be ſo,</l>
               <l>The Soule with fleſh ſhould neuer ſtriue nor once againſt it goe.</l>
               <l>But euermore in one agree. As euery power doth ſhow,</l>
               <l>That wonted are of mixed thinges, By ſpirit Diuine to grow.</l>
               <l>As in the kind of Hearbes appeares, and in the precious Stone.</l>
               <l>Some thinke the Soule doth not remaine, when fleſh from it is gone:</l>
               <l>Becauſe the heauie ſluggiſh ſleepe,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176301:60"/>the neareſt thing that may,</l>
               <l>Reſembles Death, and ſeemes to take, both Senſe and Minde away.</l>
               <l>Or for becauſe they ſee the Minde, with ſickneſſe diuerſly</l>
               <l>So vext, and harmd, that it cannot the place it hath ſupply.</l>
               <l>And with the Body to encreaſe, with which it eke decayes:</l>
               <l>As well appeares in Children young, and men of elder dayes.</l>
               <l>Fond is the child, the man diſcreete, the old man doteth ſtill:</l>
               <l>For weake vnwealdie withered age, doth Minde and Body ſpill.</l>
               <l>And more ſay they, if that the Soule, of ſubſtaunce be Diuine:</l>
               <l>And ſeuered from theſe fleſhly limmes, may lead a life more fine.</l>
               <l>Then why ſhould it in wretched fleſh, ſo ſeeke it ſelfe to place;</l>
               <l>by whoſe defect ſo many illes, and miſchifes it deface?</l>
               <l>But fond ſhe is therefore, if that ſhe doe this willingly:</l>
               <l>And if perforce ſhe be compeld in Carcaſſe caue to lie,</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:176301:61"/>
               <l>Who doth conſtraine? doth God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? then her he nought eſteemes.</l>
               <l>Nay, what in Priſon vile he puts, to hate he rather ſeemes.</l>
               <l>More, of it ſelfe (except it learne) ſith it doth nothing know,</l>
               <l>And oftentimes forgetfulneſſe the Minde doth ouerthrow:</l>
               <l>Therefore they iudge it nothing is, when Body heere doth die:</l>
               <l>For learne it cannot, ſenſes dead, which it knowes all thinges by.</l>
               <l>Some other ſay, that Soule there is in all the World but one;</l>
               <l>Which giueth life to euery thing, as Sunne, but one alone</l>
               <l>There is, that makes all eyes to ſee, Eternall thinke they this:</l>
               <l>Though Body die, or eyes put out, the Sunne eternall is.</l>
               <l>Theſe trifles fond, it is not hard, with Reaſon to diſprooue:</l>
               <l>But heere I longer am, I feare, then it doth mee behooue.</l>
               <l>There ſhall not want, that ſuch demands ſhall anſwere once at full:</l>
               <l>And all the doubtes therein aſſoyle,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176301:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>and knots aſunder pull.</l>
               <l>O man of ſharpe and pregnant wit, thy prayſe ſhall liue with mine.</l>
               <l>Our labours (doubt not) ſhall commend the men of later time.</l>
               <l>Thy famous workes attempt, and ſeedes of Heauen on Earth goe ſow:</l>
               <l>This one thing will I more put to, that euery man may know,</l>
               <l>The Soule Immortall for to be, and ſprung of Heauenly grace;</l>
               <l>If Senſes and Affections all he will reſtraine a ſpace.</l>
               <l>If that deſpiſing worldly ioyes, and earthly thought reſignde,</l>
               <l>With dayly labour he attempt, to God to lift his minde.</l>
               <l>Then perfect Wiſedome ſhall he haue, and thinges to come foretell,</l>
               <l>A wake, or elſe in heauie ſleepe, perceiue the ſame as well.</l>
               <l>In this ſort did the Prophets old, the thinges to come declare.</l>
               <l>The ſober minde therefore doth come more neare to heauenly fare,</l>
               <l>The farther from the fleſh it flies, and from the earthly care.</l>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:176301:62"/>
               <l>But like to Beaſtes the greateſt ſort doth liue, as ſenſe doth will:</l>
               <l>And thinke none other good to be, but fleſh to haue his fill.</l>
               <l>Hereof it comes that many thinke, the Soule with Body dyes:</l>
               <l>Becauſe they ſee not thinges Diui<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, with weake and fleſhly eyes.</l>
               <l>But of the Soule, this ſhall ſuffice.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Palengenius in Piſces.</head>
               <l>ANd when eſcapt from mortall chaine the Soule hath paſſage ſtraight,</l>
               <l>Conueighing with her ſelfe theſe three, that alwayes on her waite:</l>
               <l>The Minde, the Senſe, &amp; Moouing force vnto the Heauens hie;</l>
               <l>Shall ioyfull goe, and there remaine, in bliſſe perpetually.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:176301:62"/>
            <head>Matheus Dreſserus, libro de Anima.</head>
            <head>A Confirmation of the Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the Soule.</head>
            <p>THe Sentence of the Soules immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is twofold.
<list>
                  <item>1. Philoſophicall.</item>
                  <item>2. Theologicall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the opinion of Philoſophers touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Immortalitie of the Soule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some affirme, that the Soule doth die with the Body. Others do hold, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſeparation of the Body, it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth aliue, and immortall.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Argument of Panaetius.</head>
                  <l>What ſoeuer is bred, or hath a certaine beginning.</l>
                  <l>The ſame alſo dieth, or hath a cetraine ending:</l>
                  <l>But the Soule is bred, or hath a certaine beginning,</l>
                  <l>Therfore the Soule dieth, or hath a certaine ending.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Maior is to be diſtinguiſhed: for ſome thinges are bred, or haue their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Elementes, and doe die againe. But others haue a Celeſtiall and Diuine originall; as the Soule, which doth not die. Thinges that are borne,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176301:63"/>bred, or haue beginning, are of two ſortes. Some are Elementarie, ſome Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall. The Elementarie doe die or periſh: But the Celeſtiall, doe not die or periſh. But on the contrarie part, <hi>Cicero, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Xenophon,</hi> haue iudged, the Soule to be Immortall, and they prooue it thus. 1. Becauſe the originall and nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Diuine; or, as the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> ſaid, the Soule is drawen from the vniuerſall Heauenly minde. <hi>Cicero in</hi> 1 <hi>Tuſcul.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>That which is Diuine, that doth not die:</l>
               <l>The Soule is Diuine, <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Soule doth not die.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe vnto the Soule there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing mixt, nothing concrete. <hi>i.</hi> the Minde and Soule is not compounded of the Elementes: therefore it can not die with the thinges that are compounded of the Elementes.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer is compounded, the ſame is conflated or compounded of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But the Soule is not compound of the Elements:</l>
               <l>Therefore the Soule doth not die.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe the workes or effectes of the Minde are Diuine and Celeſtiall, as
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176301:63"/>to perceiue and know thinges paſt, and to come: therefore the Minde it ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, is Celeſtiall and Incorruptible.</p>
            <q>
               <l>As is the effect, ſo is the cauſe:</l>
               <l>But the effectes of the Soule are Diuine:</l>
               <l>Therefore the Soule is alſo Diuine.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="4">4 Becauſe the order of Diuine iuſtice doth require, that rewardes be giuen to Iuſt, and puniſhments to the Vniuſt. But in this life, there often chance no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes to the Iuſt, nor puniſhmentes to the Wicked: therefore after this life, there remayneth another life, wherein it ſhall goe well with the Godly, and ill with the wicked.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Exiocho</hi> ſaith; <hi>Diſceſsus ex hac vita eſt mutatio mali in bonum;</hi> that is to ſay: <hi>The departing out of this life, is a changing of euill into good.</hi> Therefore after death, the Soule alſo liueth, and ſomewhere remayneth aliue; that it may enioy that ſo great a good.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:176301:64"/>
               <head>Of the Place of the Soule after the ſeparation from the Body.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOcrates</hi> thought, that the Soule when it departeth from the Body, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to Heauen, from whence it is ſprinckled &amp; ſtrowed into mans Body. But Philoſophie doth plainely deny, and is vtterly ignoraunt, that the Soule ſhall be ioyned togeather to the Body at the vniuerſall rayſing againe of the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> alſo, although he did excellently diſpute many thinges of the Soules Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie; yet he confeſſeth, that he is in very great doubt and ſtaggering, euen as the Shippe is toſſed in the middes of the raging Seas.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Atticus</hi> ſayth, That hee, while he readeth <hi>Platos Phaedo,</hi> doth truely Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; that is to ſay, Approoue the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Immortalitie of the Soule: But when he had layde the Booke away, and beganne to cogitate with himſelfe; then that Aſſent ſlided away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates,</hi> when hee was going to his death, ſayth in <hi>Plato:</hi> It is time for mee now, to goe away from hence, that I may
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:176301:64"/>die, and you liue: but whether is better, God knoweth; I thinke truely no man knoweth.</p>
               <p>There was a Philoſopher of great Authoritie, who being called to end his life, was verie ſore vexed in minde; doubting of the flitting or departure, in what ſtate his ſoule ſhould be after death: And when he found no other Hauen, he ſent for two Philoſophers, and bade them diſpute of the condition of the Soule after the departure foorth of the Body, ſaying: Loe, I muſt flitte hence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp; forſake this mortall life: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell yee mee, what ſhall become of mee; whether my Soule ſhall liue, when this Body is extinct, or no? for vnleſſe this can be prooued vnto me, and I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in perſwaded, with what minde can I depart out of this life? Heere the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers began ſharply to contende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Nature of the Soule: and the one reaſon'd it to be Mortall, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Immortall. And when they had a long time diſputed, neither part preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: Goe to, ſayth the ſicke man, all ſorrowfull, I ſhall now prooue, whether
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:176301:65"/>of you doth thinke more rightly.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Theologie</hi> doth diſcreetly affirme, both that the Soule is Immortall, and alſo that it ſhall at length, returne into the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Body: &amp; doth name the very place alſo, wherein the Soule ſhall remaine &amp; be kept, vntill the laſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>That the Soule doth not die, is thus prooued by the holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BEcauſe it is a Spirit; which cannot die. <hi>Gen. 2. Math. 10.</hi> Doe not feare thoſe that can kill the Body, but cannot kill the Soule. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. Hee breathed into him the breath of life.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe; God is the God of the liuing. God is the God of. <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> liueth, although his body be dead. <hi>Mat. 22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 From Examples. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with Chriſt in Mount <hi>Thabor. Luk. 9.</hi> although <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead a thouſand and fiue hundred yeares before: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they liue.</p>
               <p n="4">4 From the teſtimonie of Chriſt. <hi>Ion. 11.</hi> Hee that beleeueth in me, he ſhall
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176301:65"/>not die for euer. Therefore the Soule is not extinguiſhed, but liueth alwayes.</p>
               <p n="5">5 There is alſo a firme Argument from the Cauſe vnto the Effect, or from the nature of Relatiues.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Chriſt is riſen, and liueth.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt is our Author and Head.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Therefore we alſo ſhall riſe againe: And the Soule at length, coupled with the Body ſhall liue for euer.</p>
               <p>For what is of force in Chriſt, the ſame muſt needes alſo auaile in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. <hi>1. Cor. 15.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that the Body being renewed, ſhall of vs be recciued againe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, the teſtimonie of <hi>Job</hi> in the 19, chap. teacheth plainely. I know that my Redeemer liueth; and that I ſhall riſe againe out of the Earth in the laſt day and ſhall ſee God in my fleſh.</p>
               <p>The Place or Seate into the which the Soule doth flitte, being looſed from the fetters of the Body, and reſteth in the ſame, is called, Paradiſe. <hi>Luk. 23.</hi> The boſome of <hi>Abraham, Luk. 16.</hi> The hand of God <hi>Sap. 3.</hi> Scheol. <hi>1.</hi> Hell <hi>Gen. 43.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:176301:66"/>
               <head>The Immortalitie of the Soule prooued by manifeſt places of the holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Numbers 23.10.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Pray God I may die the death of the Righteous; and let my laſt end be like his.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Pſal 84.1, 2, 4, 10.</p>
               <p n="1">1. O how amiable are thy Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, o Lord of Hoſtes?</p>
               <p n="2">2. My Soule longeth, yea and fainteth for the Courtes of the Lord: for my heart and my fleſh reioyce in the liuing God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy Houſe: they will euer praiſe thee. <hi>Selah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. One day in thy Courtes is better, then a thouſand other where. I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a Dore-keeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ejay. 51.6.11.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Lift vp your eyes to the Heauens, and looke vpon the Earth beneath: for the Heauens ſhall vaniſh away like ſmoake, and the Earth ſhall waxe old like a garment, and they that dwel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:176301:66"/>ſhall periſh in like maner: but my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation ſhalbe for euer, and my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall not be aboliſhed.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The redeemed of the Lord ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and come with ioy vnto Zion, and euerlaſting ioy ſhalbe vpon their head; they ſhall obtaine ioy and gladneſſe, and ſorrow and mourning ſhalbe away.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Eſaj.</hi> 32.18.</p>
               <p>My people ſhall dwell in peace, and in ſure dwellinges, &amp; in ſafe reſting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: in aſſurance for euer.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Eſaj.</hi> 49.10.</p>
               <p>They ſhall not be hungry, neither ſhall they be thirſtie; neither ſhall the heate ſmite them nor the Sunne: for he that hath compaſsion on them, ſhall lead them; euen to the ſpringes of waters ſhall he driue them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Eſaj. 65.17.18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 Loe, I will create new Heauens and a new Earth; and the former ſhall not be remembred, nor come into minde.</p>
               <p n="18">18 But be you glad and reioyce for euer in the thinges that I ſhall create.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Dan. 12 1.2.3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And at that time ſhall <hi>Michael</hi> ſtand
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:176301:67"/>vp, the great Prince, which ſtandeth for the children of thy people, and there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as neuer was ſince the time that there began to be a Nation, vntill the ſame time. And at that time, thy people ſhall be deliuered, euery one that ſhall be found written in the Booke.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And many of them, that ſleepe in the duſt of the Earth, ſhall awake; ſome to euerlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and perpetuall contempt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And they that be wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the Firmament: and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the Starres, for euer &amp; euer.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>2. Eſaras. 2.35.36.37.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be readie to the reward of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: for the euerlaſting light ſhall ſhine vpon you for euermore.</p>
               <p n="36">36 Flee the ſhadow of this world: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ioy of your glorie; I teſtifie my Sauiour openly.</p>
               <p n="37">37 Receiue the gift that is giuen you, and be glad: giuing thankes vnto him that hath called you to the Heauenly kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:176301:67"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Sap. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soules of the righteous, are in the hand of God; and the paine of death ſhall not touch them.</p>
               <p>In the ſight of the vnwiſe, they appeare to die, &amp;c. Yet is their hope full of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Sap. 5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Faythfull are counted among the Children of God, and their portion is among the Saintes. The Righteous ſhall liue for euermore: their reward alſo is with the Lord, and their remembraunce with the higheſt. Therefore ſhall they receiue a glorious Kingdome, &amp; a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Crowne of the Lords hand.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Tob.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>O Lord, deale with me according to thy will, and commaund my ſpirit to be receiued in peace.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes. 7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The day of death is better then the day of birth. For precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of this Saintes, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the <hi>116. Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Mat. 13.43.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſhall the Iuſt men ſhine as the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:176301:68"/>Sunne, in the Kingdome of their father.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Mat. 19.29.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſhall inherite euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Mat. 25.34.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come ye bleſſed Children of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherite the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Mat. 22.29.30.31.32.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29 Yee are deceiued, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God.</p>
               <p n="30">30 For in the Reſurrection, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marrie Wiues, nor Wiues are beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in marriage; but are as the Angels of God in Heauen.</p>
               <p n="31">31 And concerning the Reſurrection of the dead, haue yee not read what is ſpoken vnto you of God, ſaying:</p>
               <p n="32">32 I am the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iacob;</hi> God is not the God of the dead, but of the liuing.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>The ſame is recorded in the 12. of Marke, verſ. 24, 25, 26, 27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all which places, it is a plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, that the Soule is Immortall.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Luk. 16.22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lazarus</hi> is ſaid to be caried into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Boſome. Now what <hi>Abrahams</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:176301:68"/>Boſome is, let venerable <hi>Beda</hi> witneſſe againſt the Papiſtes, that ſo much boaſt of him: who in his Homilie on the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell for the firſt Sunday after <hi>Trinitie,</hi> writeth thus. <hi>Sinus Abraham requies hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum pauperum, quorum eſt regnum coelorum, quo poſt hanc vitam recipiuntur:</hi> That is; Abrahams <hi>Boſome, is the reſt of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed poore; whoſe is the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whither after this life, they are receiued.</hi> So by the iudgement of <hi>Beda</hi> (agreeing with the trueth,) <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſome, is the Kingdome of Heauen, with <hi>Lazarus</hi> was caried. Out of the ſame place alſo it is apparent concerning the Soules of the Wicked: For the Rich Glutton is ſayd on the contrarie, to be carried downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell. Therefore the Soules liue after the Body.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Luk. 23.43.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt hanging on the Croſſe, ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Thiefe; This day ſhalt thou be with mee in Paradiſe. Now that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe is Heauen, is prooued by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>2. Cor. 12. 1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> where he ſayth, He was taken vp into the third Heauen: which hee calleth Paradiſe. But the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176301:69"/>Thiefe could not be with Chriſt in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe in the Body; becauſe that was dead &amp; buried. Therefore his Soule was with Chriſts in Paradiſe: and ſo conſequently the Soule liueth, and is Immortall.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Luk. 23.46.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Father, into thy hands I commende my ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>John. 16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your ioy ſhall no man take from you.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>John. 5.24.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee that heareth my word, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him that ſent me, hath euerlaſting life, &amp; ſhal not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death to life.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Joe.</hi> 6.54.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer eateth my fleſh and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth my Blood, hath eternall life; and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day.</p>
               <p n="24">24. <hi>Joh. 11.26.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who ſoeuer liueth and beleeueth in mee, ſhall neuer die.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>1. Cor. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, neither can it enter into mans heart, what thinges God hath prepared for them that loue him.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:176301:69"/>
               <p n="26">26. 2. <hi>Cor. 5.8.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 We loue rather to remoue out of the Body, &amp; to dwell with the Lord: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Soules ſleepe not, as ſome Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes will haue them; but inioy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall life, &amp; celeſtiall glory with God.</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>Phil. 1.23.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire to be looſed, and to be with Chriſt. He ſpeaketh of the reſt and ioy, which he ſhould inioy with Chriſt. But they who feele nothing, what can their ioy or happineſſe be? Wherefore they alſo are refuted in this poynt, that ſay, That mens Soules ſleepe, and ſo withall, denie the Immortalitie of the Soule.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>1. Theſ. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſhall we euer be with the Lord.</p>
               <p n="29">29. <hi>Reuel. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To him that ouercommeth, will I giue to eate of the Tree of Life, which is in the middeſt of the Paradiſe of God.</p>
               <p>Be faythfull vnto the death, and I ſhall giue thee the Crowne of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reue. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Him that ouercommeth, will I make a Pillar in the Temple of God; and he ſhall goe no more out.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:176301:70"/>
               <p>To him that ouercommeth, will I graunt to ſit with me in my ſeate.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>Reu. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 24. Elders that ſate on the Seates, were clothed in White rayment, and had on their heades Crownes of Gold.</p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Reu. 7.15, 16, 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 They are in the preſence of the Throne of God, and ſerue him day and night in his Temple; and he that ſitteth on the Throne, will dwell among them.</p>
               <p n="16">16 They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sunne light on them, neither any heate.</p>
               <p n="17">17 For the Lame, which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Throne, ſhall gouerne them, and ſhall lead them vnto the liuely Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of waters: and God ſhall wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all teares from their eyes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cor. 15.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If in this life onely we hope in Chriſt, then are we moſt miſerable of all men.</p>
               <p>If Chriſtians in this life onely, do hope in Chriſt: 1. If they hope of Chriſt for the bleſſedneſſe of this life onely, and not of one to come, then are they moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of all men. But Chriſtians are not
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:176301:70"/>moſt miſerable of all men: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they do not looke or hope of Chriſt for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of this life onely, but alſo of the life to come: and by a conſequent they ſhall riſe from the dead, that they may be partakers of that bleſſedneſſe in an other life.</p>
               <p>Theſe teſtimonies of Scriptures, doe teach and confirme moſt euidently, that not onely in the Body before death, and after the reſurrection of the Body; but alſo in the whole ſpace and time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming betweene, the Soules are, liue, feele, vnderſtand, out of the Body; though the manner of their operations be to vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. Wherefore alſo this gift of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, hath ſome ſimilitude with God; who alone, is the onely fountaine of life, hath Immortalitie: as ſayth <hi>Paul</hi> 1, <hi>Tim. 6.16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Aduerſaries of this Trueth, the deare dearelings of the Diuell, fighting with weapons of their graund Captaine <hi>Sathan;</hi> euen as he in tempting our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, wreſted the Scriptures to his purpoſe: euen ſo they peruerting the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:176301:71"/>true ſenſe, alleadge ſundry places of the Scriptures to diſprooue the Immortalitie of the Soule, and to approoue their owne wicked aſſertion, that the Soule is Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. Of which helliſh Champions, and their vaine and wicked, not reaſons, but wordes, I with a reproofe, will bring a double diſproofe, and ſo thereby giue our ſide a ſtronger approofe, by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preating their falſe alleadged places, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the right ſenſe and meaning.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Gen. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the day that thou eateſt of the Tree of knowledge of Good and Euill, thou ſhalt die the death. Loe, (ſay they) the death of Body and Soule both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere, interpreating the place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord in this Scripture, doth not threaten to Man, the deſtruction or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing of his Soule, but eternall Death; that is, the horrible feeling and terrour of Gods wrath and iudgement, and to liue forſaken and caſt off from God, ſubiect to all miſeries &amp; torments: vnto the which eternall death the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and parting aſunder of the Soule
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:176301:71"/>and Body by temporall death, is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct; which at that time, through Gods mercie was deferred, that, that mankind might be ſaued: For ſo was <hi>Adam</hi> dead, while he yet liued in Paradiſe, euen ſo ſoone as euer he had eaten the forbidden Fruite: So in eternall death liue all the damned and reprobate; whoſe Fire ſhall not be put out, and their Worme ſhall neuer die. So in the ſecond to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> are they ſayd, To be dead through ſinne, that liue in ſinne without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And <hi>Epheſ. 5.</hi> Hee who from ſinne is reclaymed to God, is willed to riſe from the dead. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That through the knowledge of ſinne and the wrath of God, hee was dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Eccles. 3.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19 The condition of the Children of men, and the condition of Beaſtes, are euen as one condition to them. As the one dyeth, ſo dyeth the other: for they haue all one breath; and there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of Man aboue the Beaſt: for all is Vanitie.</p>
               <p n="20">20 All goe to one place, and all was duſt, &amp; ſhall returne to the duſt. Therfore
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:176301:72"/>the Soule is not Immortall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere interpreating.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere they are deceiued by a fallation, taking that to be ſpoken ſimply, which is but, <hi>ſecundum quid, i. <hi>in ſome fort, or, in ſome reſpect.</hi>
                  </hi> For the <hi>Preacher</hi> doth not ſimply ſay, That Men die as Beaſtes, and ſo doe vtterly periſh: for this ſenſe cantradicteth other Scriptures. But in two reſpectes, the death of Men, and the death of Beaſtes, are like. 1. Becauſe Men muſt needes once die and depart out of this life; becauſe Men are not heere to continue for euer, nor haue heere a ſetled place. 2. Men die as Beaſtes; that is, In the ſenſe and iudgement of the Wicked, they ſeeme to periſh.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Pſal. 78.39.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee remembred that they were but fleſh: yea, a winde that paſſeth away, and commeth not againe. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Mortall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe, and ſuch like ſpeaches, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and be wayled the frayltie of all humaine affaires, that with God doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and come to nothing. For as in this place, they are likened to a Winde that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:176301:72"/>ſoone vaniſheth away: ſo in <hi>Pſal. 103.</hi> they are compared to Duſt, Earth, and Flowers of the field. So <hi>Iob.</hi> 14. Man commeth vp as a Flower, and is cutte downe. <hi>Iſa. 40.6.</hi> All fleſh is graſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Pſal. 88.5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am counted as ſlaine lying in the Graue; whom thou remembreſt no more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe wordes, the Pſalmiſt doth not meane, that either hee himſelfe, or the dead, are exempted from Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. But hee complayneth that hee is forſaken of God, euen as it ſeemeth to men, that God careth not for the dead. And therefore hee ſpeaketh not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſenſe of Fayth, but of his owne opinion, weakneſſe, and miſerie, who iudgeth thoſe thinges to be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kèn and neglected of God, whoſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie for a while he doth deferre.</p>
               <p>But what Fayth in the meane ſeaſon doth ſuggeſt and tell the Godly, euen when they ſtriue and wraſtle with temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? he ſheweth in the <hi>ii. Pſal.</hi> and verſ 2. The iuſt ſhall be had in an euerlaſting
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:176301:73"/>remembrance.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Pſal. 146.4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Spirit departeth, and returneth to his earth; and then all his thoughtes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Ergo. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee doth not heere ſay, That the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Soule of men doth not die, or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, or is bereaued of ſenſe: But, that it departeth; to witte, from the Body, wherein it dwelleth: and that not the Spirit, but the Body, returneth to earth, which was made of earth. And where he ſayth, That all his thoughtes periſh: he meaneth not, that the Soule is after this life, bereaued of Reaſon, Iudgement, and Senſe of Gods mercie, or wrath; but that mans Purpoſes and Counſailes are made fruſtrate, which in his life he had ſetled him ſelfe to bring to paſſe: In which ſenſe it is ſayd in <hi>Pſal. 112.10.</hi> The deſire of the Wicked ſhall periſh.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Pſal. 88.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou ſhew a miracle to the dead? Or, ſhall the dead riſe, and prayſe thee? Whereunto we adde all ſuch places as take away worſhipping of God from
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:176301:73"/>the dead, which muſt needes prooue the Soule not Immortall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſuch ſpeaches, Death and Hell, or the Graue, haue two ſignifications. They who are ſpiritually dead, whether before or after the death of the Body; that is, they that are depriued of Gods grace, and forſaken and reiected of God, and are in Hell, that is, in the place and tormentes of the Damned; or elſe in this life, deſpayring and deſtitute of comfort, ſhall not prayſe God at all, neither in this life, nor in the life to come. But they who are dead not ſpiritually, but corporally onely, although they ſhall not prayſe God while their Bodyes are in Hell, that is, in the Graue, (for which this word Hell, is often vſed in the Scriptures;) yet in Soule they ſhall not ceaſſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prayſe God, vntill, when they haue receiued their Bodyes againe, they ſhall magnifie him both in Soule and Body, in the Celeſtiall eternitie.</p>
               <p>But in the meane time, ſith God will be acknowledged and magnified of men in this life alſo, therefore both the whole
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:176301:74"/>Church, and euery one of the faythfull, not onely pray that they may not fall into that forſaking, and that ſenſe of Gods wrath, wherewith the Wicked are oppreſſed, but alſo deſire, that they may be preſerued and defended in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life, vntill the end thereof appoynted by God, be expired: for the Saintes doe not ſimply ſtand in feare of the bodily Death and Graue; but that they may not be forſaken of God, neither fall into deſperation or deſtruction, or their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies inſult againſt God, when they are ouerthrowne. This with dayly and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent prayers and petitions, they begge and craue continually.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Pſal. 146.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>I will prayſe the Lord during my life: as long as I haue any beeing, I will ſing vnto my God. Heere hee reſtreyneth prayſes to this life onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This place, maketh nothing to the purpoſe: For he doth not limit prayſes to this life; but this he onely ſayth, that he will ſpend all the time of this mortall life in Gods prayſes: which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:176301:74"/>in many other places he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to continuall eternitie; as <hi>Pſal. 34.</hi> I will prayſe the Lord continually. But often times this particle, <hi>Vntill,</hi> or, <hi>As long,</hi> ſignifieth a continuance of the time going before ſome euent, without any excluding of the time following: as <hi>1. Cor. 15.25.</hi> Hee muſt raigne, <hi>Vntill</hi> hee hath put all his enimies vnder his feete, I thinke they will not ſay, that when Chriſtes enimies are put vnder his feete, that then he ſhall raigne no longer.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Job. 10.20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let him ceaſſe and leaue off from mee, that I may take a little comfort before I goe, and ſhall not returne: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Soule is Mortall; there is no Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe wordes, he denyeth that hee ſhall returne into this Mortall life, and conuerſe amongſt men in this World: But he denieth not that he in the meane ſeaſon, hath his beeing, and doth liue, vntill againe he ſee God in the fleſh; euen the ſame <hi>Iob,</hi> who then was afflicted: as himſelfe ſayth. <hi>chap. 19.26.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:176301:75"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Iob. 3.11.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why died I not when I came out of the Wombe? ſo ſhould I haue lyen qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and been at reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> in theſe wordes, doth not denie, that the Soules after death doe liue, feele, and vnderſtand: but onely he ſayth; the Miſeries of this preſent life are not felt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> would not wiſh for a bad change: but if there be euils felt in the life to come, hee wiſhed for a badde change: <hi>Ergo. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> wiſhed not for the death of the wicked, but of the godly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Job</hi> maketh Kinges and Princes alſo, which gather Gold vnto them. <hi>verſ. 14.15.</hi> ſmall and great, good and badde. <hi>verſ. 16, 17, 18, 19.</hi> partakers of this reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It plainely appeareth out of the whole proceſſe and diſcourſe of <hi>Jobs</hi> wordes, that he doth not teach what is the ſtate of men after this life; but onely deſireth
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:176301:75"/>to be ridde out of his preſent miſerie. And therefore through humaine infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and impatience, he compareth the ſenſe and feeling of his preſent miſeries with the death and ſtate of the Dead, whatſoeuer it be. As they who are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tormented with preſent Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Calamities, preferre any thing whatſoeuer, before that which they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. So alſo he ſayth in the <hi>7. chap.</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as one deſpayring of deliuerie in this life: <hi>Remember that my life is but a winde, and that mine eye ſhall not returne to ſee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> For ſo hee expoundeth himſelfe, when hee addeth, <hi>verſ. 10.</hi> Hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne no more to his houſe, neither ſhall his place know him any more. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the <hi>17. chap.</hi> My breath is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, my dayes are corrupt, &amp; the Graue is readie for mee. They are wordes of one deſpayring of life &amp; ſaluation, God being wroth and angrie.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Job. 34.14.15.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 If he ſet his heart vpon man, and gather vnto himſelfe his ſpirit and his breath. 15. All fleſh ſhall periſh togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and man ſhall returne vnto duſt.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:176301:76"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> doth not heere ſay, that the Soule doth either ſleepe, or periſh: but that by the departure of the Soule from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the Bodie dieth and is diſſolued: yet not that the Body doth vtterly periſh; for ſo it ſhould repugne other plaine places that warrant the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Job. 14.12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Man ſleepeth, and riſeth not; for hee ſhall not wake againe, nor be raiſed from his ſleepe, till the Heauen be no more.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Act. 7.60.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when he had thus ſpoken, he fell aſleepe.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>1. Cor. 15.51.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſhall not all ſleepe, but we ſhalbe all changed.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>1. Theſ. 4.13.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not haue you ignoraunt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them which are aſleepe. In theſe places, the dead are ſayd to ſleepe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Soule ſleepeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe and ſuch like places, is vſed a figure of ſpeach called, <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating that which is proper vnto the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:176301:76"/>to the whole man. For that this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the Body, which is to be recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from death to life, as it were to awake from ſleepe; many places of Scripture declare: As <hi>Iob. 7.</hi> Behold now I ſleepe in the duſt. For not the Soule, but the Body onely ſleepeth in the duſt or Graue.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Mat. 24.46.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed is that Seruant, whom his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, when he commeth, ſhall find ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Mat. 25.34.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Mark. 13.13.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 And yee ſhalbe hated of all men for my names ſake. But whoſoeuer ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure vnto the ende, the ſame ſhall be ſaued.</p>
               <p n="27">27 And he ſhall then ſend his Angles, and gather to geather his elect, from the foure Windes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Dan. 12.1.2.</p>
               <p>1 And at that time, my people ſhalbe deliuered, euery one that ſhalbe found written in the Booke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:176301:77"/>2 And many of them that ſleepe in the duſt of the earth, ſhall awake, ſome to euerlaſting life, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe places doe plainely ſhew, that Bleſſedneſſe, and the Kingdome promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the godly, ſhall then firſt fall vnto them at the laſt day: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Soules go not preſently to heauen after death of the Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe places doe not ſhew that: But they ſhew, that at the laſt day, when the Bodies ſhalbe raiſed vp againe, the Soules that alreadie are in Heauen, ſhall by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned to the bodyes againe, haue their felicitie and glory conſummated, and made abſolute. For ſo we pray; <hi>Thy Kingdome come:</hi> when yet now, God alſo raigneth in vs.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>1. Cor. 15.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If in this life onely we haue Hope, we are of all men moſt miſerable. Of this place, they reaſon thus.</p>
               <p>Hee that is bleſſed and happy before the Reſurrection, is not without the Reſurrection moſt miſerable.</p>
               <p>But wee without the Reſurrection,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:176301:77"/>ſhould be of all men moſt miſerable; <hi>Ergo,</hi> wee are not before the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, bleſſed and happie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the Maior we anſwere: That he is not miſerable without the Reſurrection, who can not onely before it, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it alſo, be bleſſed: But we are in ſuch wiſe bleſſed before it, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding without it following and enſuing, we can not enioy that former bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: becauſe, that God with ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a knot hath ioyned togeather the beginning, &amp; proceeding, and finiſhing or perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Electes bleſſedneſſe; that none can haue the beginning, who muſt not come to the end and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof. Wherefore we muſt riſe againe, or we muſt want alſo the Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bleſſedneſſe before the Reſurrection. <hi>Rom. 8.11.</hi> If the ſpirit of him that rayſed vp Ieſus from the dead, dwell in you; hee that rayſed vp Chriſt from the dead, ſhall alſo quicken your mortall Bodies.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Heb. 11.39.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe all through Fayth are dead, and receiued not the Promiſe. Therefore
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:176301:78"/>they receiued not their Countrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although when they died, they had not found their Countrie; yet would it not follow of theſe wordes, that they are not at all, or haue no ſenſe after death: for he that is not, or hath no ſenſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not his Countrie. Secondly, it is not there ſpoken of the life after death, which is ledde in the Celeſtiall countrie, ſpoken of in <hi>2. Cor. 5.</hi> from <hi>verſ. 1.</hi> vnto <hi>10.</hi> but of this life; in which the faythfull walking their pilgrimage, ſought for the Celeſtiall countrie, not finding their Countrie on Earth.</p>
               <p n="21">21. If preſently after death, the godly were bleſſed; then iniurie was done vnto them, who were called againe into this mortall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was not iniurions to them, ſeeing God is debtor to no man. God did raiſe them vp for the manifeſting of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Now what can happen better, or more acceptable vnto the Godly, then to ſerue for the manifeſting of his glory,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:176301:78"/>either by life or by death? Therefore there was no iniurie done vnto them. <hi>Phil. 1.</hi> As alwayes, ſo now, Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my Body, whether it be by life or by death. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The Soule hath neither ſenſe nor acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by bodily inſtrumentes; and therefore being naked of thoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, it is alſo deſtitute of ſenſe, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and operation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſweré.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although we graunt the Antecedent that the Soules action and ſenſe is by the inſtrumentes of the Body, while it is in the Body before this naturall or corporal death; yet notwithſtanding that it is not ſo with the Soule after death, when it is freed from the Body, both learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers doe confeſſe, and the word of God teſtifieth. <hi>1. Cor. 13.9.</hi> Wee know in part, and wee prophecie in part: but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhalbe aboliſhed.</p>
               <p>¶ Thus (I hope) are ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooned thoſe wicked Aduerſaries of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:176301:79"/>this knowne and neceſſarie Trueth, <hi>The Soule is Immortall.</hi> And the Scriptures falſely by them alleadged, rightly and fully interpreted according to their true ſenſe. By which reproofe of the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, and diſproofe of their cauſe, the trueth is more approoued, and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier confirmed: For contraries by their contraries, are euer made more manifeſt. God giue the Trueth a ſpeedie victorie in the heartes of his people, that Errours may be beaten downe, Sathan confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and all our Enimies vanquiſhed; that we may triumph with our Captaine that Lion of the Tribe of <hi>luda,</hi> our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:176301:79"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Athenagoras</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> and a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Philoſopher, flouriſhed in the time of <hi>Marcus Aurelius, Antoninus,</hi> and <hi>Commodus,</hi> Emperours of Rome, within two hundred yeares after Chriſt: and in his Booke of the Reſurrection, he reaſoueth thus.</head>
            <p>REaſons touching thinges belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mankind, are ſome drawne from Naturall order, ſome from the order of Gods Prouidence; ſuch as are the reaſons concerning the Reſurrection of the Dead. If then wee can prooue, that God is able to know this, and to will it, we ſhall then euen in a manner, prooue the thing itſelfe.</p>
            <p>God before he made Man, knew the whole World, and all the partes thereof; and how to order, mixe, and compound the Elementes one with another, in the workemanſhippe of euerie ſeuerall man. In like manner, when he diſſolueth his worke, he vnderſtandeth whither, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:176301:80"/>vnto what eſtate euery part and parcell thereof ſhall come, at the laſt. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knoweth from whence they are in like manner to be taken againe, and by what meanes they are to be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the ſame forme they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and how to compounde the ſame man againe. God his cunning &amp; might is the ſame that was. And euen as he was alſo able to make that which hee knew from the beginning; ſo that which hee yet knoweth, is hee in like manner able to make new againe. God, ſeeing that he is Wiſedome it ſelfe, did therefore make nothing in vaine. Hee did not in vaine make Man partaker of Wiſedome: therefore to ſome certaine end: But not vnto this end, that thinges either aboue, or beneath vs, ſhould vſe Man to their owne behoofe: for thoſe thinges ſtand no need of this vſe, but rather were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues for our vſe. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made Man for himſelfe, and for the contemplation of Gods Goodneſſe and Wiſedome in his whole workemanſhip. God indeed made Man to the end hee might liue; but yet not to be vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:176301:80"/>like vnto Beaſtes: for vnto this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creature, that heareth within it ſelfe, the ſimilitude of God it author, by the Vnderſtanding and Reaſon, hath God giuen Euerlaſting life. For verily bruite Beaſtes were not created for themſelues, but for the vſe of others: which when it ceaſeth, the preſeruation or reſtitution of them is not any more neceſſarie. But Men were not ſo created, that they ſhould ſerue for the vſe of others; but that their life might ſo be continued, that they conſidering the Might and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their Author, and keeping his Lawes, might enioy Euerlaſting life, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with thoſe with whom they lead their liues from the beginning. For God verily gaue vnto Man a nature that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of a Soule immortall; and ſuch a Body, as might vnite it ſelfe to ſuch a Soule contemplating Heauenly thinges, and imitating God, by the keeping of his heauenly Lawes. This Acte therefore concerneth Eternitie. This end conſtitute in the inmoſt Act, declareth that Man ſhalbe euerlaſting: to witte, in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which conduceth vnto ſuch like
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:176301:81"/>Act, by the coupling togeather of the Soule and of the Body. Which, if at any time it be diſſolued, is to be reſtored by the Reſurrection, hoped for of vs, not through a vaine Hope, but through Fayth, a moſt certaine ſure commander; to wit, through Gods determinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, creating ſuch like nature of man to ſuch like euerlaſting end and office. God hath not appoynted to any other vſe, but hath ordained him according to the inward act of his nature, to imitate God by the contemplation and obſeruation of Heauenly thinges. Which end aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, ſeeing it is the inmoſt in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and diracted to euerlaſtingnes, doth declare, that Man ſhalbe euerlaſting: Man I ſay, not the Soule onely; but the whole, compounded of Soule and Body: For God, to conſtitute this, brought to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather the Soule and Body, as partes. The procreation of mans compoſition, is the nature and common life of the man compounded, gathered of the actions and paſsions as well of Body as Soule: The end therefore of the compound, is <hi>commune;</hi> that is to ſay, the imitating
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:176301:81"/>of God, and the enioying of him by the ſame. Gods Iuſtice alſo muſt draw vnto Iudgement both Soule &amp; Body, to beare the reward or puniſhment, according to the action &amp; paſsion, and common life. And the end can not be common and one, &amp; iuſtly exhibited, vnleſſe it ſhould belong vnto one commonthing, and that to be men, who commonly had wrought it: And to this, is neceſſarie the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead.</p>
            <p>God hath giuen to man, the iudgement of Vnderſtanding and reaſon, that he may know thoſe thinges that may be vnderſtood concerning God; to witte, his Goodneſſe, Wiſedome, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. Seeing then, that theſe are ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piternall; it followeth, that man alſo is borne to thinges ſempiternall, and ſhall be ſempiternall: Man I ſay, compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; for vnto him is giuen the vſe of Iudgement, the office of Virtues, and imitation of Heauenly thinges. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he ſhould remaine compound, ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vſe &amp; office, ſhould not alway con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. And it cannot be, that Man can be euerlaſting, if he riſe not againe from
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:176301:82"/>death. And vnleſſe Man ſhould be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, raſhly and in vaine ſhould the Soule of the Body be ioyned to ſo many wantes and innumerable paſsions. In vaine ſhould the Body be withdrawne by Reaſon, from following delightes &amp; pleaſures: vaine &amp; raſh ſhould be the painefull vſe of Virtues, and the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſeruation of Iuſtice and Lawes. Thoſe Creatures, that haue their perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce euerlaſting, doe differ therein, according to the diuerſitie of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Angels haue it immoueably; the Heauenly bodyes moueably, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: But Men, moueably &amp; interrupt. The Soule truely hath a continuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance; the Body a life left for a time: but ſo hath not a bruite Beaſt. For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nature of the Body, wee dayly wayting, doe feare a diſſolution: but according to the Nature of the Soule, vſe of Virtues, and knowledge of the Creator, we looke for the Reſurrection of the Body. Moreouer, we doe no leſſe, for all this, call the life of the Body, Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piternall; for that, for a time, it lieth dead, through the ſeparation of the Soule. As
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:176301:82"/>alſo, we call euery mans life, vntill his death, one and continuall; although it ſeeme by the courſe of times as it were, cut off; &amp; through the changing of ages, to be in like manner changed.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>That the Reſurrection, is of Gods Prouidence and Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>GOD, by the ſame Wiſdome that he made and maketh all thinges, doth alſo dayly and hourely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for euery thing: And by that Iuſtice that he placed ſeuerall degrees in the World, by the ſame, doth he giue euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to euery thing, the things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it. This prouidence prouideth for man, compounded of Soule and Body, nouriſhment &amp; ſucceſsion: And in like manner for Man compounded, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth Iudgement, iuſtly to diſpence the common reward or puniſhment, for the actions or paſsions common to Soule and Body. But ſuch-like Iudgement is leſſe fulfilled in this preſent life, where the Wicked for the moſt part, are proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, and the Godly and Righteous,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:176301:83"/>almoſt alwayes in aduerſitie. Neither in the other life, can this Iudgement be fulfilled, diſtributing iuſtly thinges that are common, vnleſſe there may follow the Reſurrection of the Bodies. The Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (verily) as it hath been the fellow of the Soule in all actions and paſsions, as well of Virtues as of Vices; and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Holyneſſe and Martirdome: ſo ought it alſo to haue like lot in Paine or Rewarde; therefore the fame Body muſt ariſe againe. For vnleſſe there remained rewardes of the life to come, Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and Iuſtice might be had in doubt; yea, and Man ſhould be more miſerable then bruite Beaſtes, who for Religion &amp; Iuſtice ſake, depriueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of bodily delights, &amp; hazardeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in innumerable daungers: yea, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue her ſelfe, Religion, and Lawes, ſhould be dotinges and detrimentes. Vnleſſe the Bodies rife againe, Gods Iuſtice hath no place in the Soule and body. Not in the Body: becauſe it ſhould be vniuſt for the Soule to haue reward of thoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wherein the Body ſuffered a great part, and cannot it ſelfe haue part in that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:176301:83"/>reward. Not in the Soule: becauſe it ſhould be vniuſt for the Soule alone to ſuffer puniſhment for ſo many grieuous ſinnes, which of it ſelfe it had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, if the Body had not been ioyned vnto it: for thorow the meanes of the Body, euen of neceſsitie, Pleaſure and Paſsion, it abideth many ſharpe ſhowers or perturbations, and ſinneth very often. Vices are not of the Soule only; but are in the whole Man, drawne from the wantes of the Body, and prouoking of the ſame. In like manner are Virtues in the Whole man; for if the Soule had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come into the Body, it ſhould not haue needed Fortitude, Continencie, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, Counſell in matters of affaires, and the like Iuſtice. Virtues then are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed: from hence truly in the Soule, but from thence in the Body, becauſe that all men doe confeſſe, that Virtues (at the leaſtwiſe thoſe that are Morall) are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine inuringes of our Soule and Body. Then it is not iuſt for the Soule alone, to haue either, the puniſhment of Vices, or reward of Virtues. The Lawes giuen from Heauen, are not giuen to the Soule
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:176301:84"/>onely, but to Man alſo: For there was no need to affray the Soule from Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Man ſlaughter, Theft, and ſuch like thinges, which belong onely to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; bodily vſe. The whole man then, that is tyed to the Lawes, muſt iuſtly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receiue reward for keeping of the Lawes, or elſe puniſhment for omitting his duetie. Seeing that all thinges euery one, haue their proper endes, according to the diuerſitie of their Natures, it muſt needes be, that this Nature indued with Reaſon, ſhould alſo obtaine her proper end. But this end is not lacke of paine; for that is alſo common to other Bodies without life: Neither againe, is it a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall delight; for that is common to bruit Beaſtes: but it is rather ſomewhat agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the proper and chiefe nature, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and action thereof; that is to ſay, reaſonable and intellectuall; a precept wherein continually to reſt, and in which eſtate, Virtue her ſelfe may enioy her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes: Such like end, in this preſent life, we can neuer attaine; therefore in the life to come. But ſeeing there is an end of humaine life and actions, and that
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:176301:84"/>this life and actions, are common to the whole man; it muſt needes follow, that that end muſt needs belong to the whole man. By the which conſequence, wee may ſurely know that there ſhalbe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: eſpecially becauſe that our Heauenly workeman hath made all thinges for himſelfe: therefore hath he giuen vnto vs, from the beginning, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Vnderſtanding, able to regard Heauenly things, that we might contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate him, or behold him in his workes. From whence is concluded, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of God, is the firme and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute end of Man.</p>
               <p>Theſe thinges haue we briefly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Reſurrection, not purpoſing hereby eloquently to ſet foorth al things that may hereof be ſpoken: but euen a few, ſuch as are moſt fit for the time, which the hearers may very eaſily learne.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:176301:85"/>
            <head>A Booke of <hi>Xenocrates,</hi> a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher of <hi>Plato</hi> his ſect, <hi>concerning Death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The ſpeakers are, <hi>Socrates, Clinias,</hi> and <hi>Axiochus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVHen I went vnto <hi>Cynoſarges,</hi> and was now come to <hi>Iliſſum,</hi> I heard ones voyce calling me by names; And turning my ſelfe, I ſaw <hi>Clinias,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Axiochus,</hi> running toward the Well <hi>Calliroe;</hi> and togeather with him, <hi>Damon</hi> the Muſition, and <hi>Carmides</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Glancus,</hi> of whom that ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent cunning Muſition, was my very deare and eſpeciall friend: Therefore I thought good to goe backe againe and meete them, that we might more leaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eaſily goe togeather: But <hi>Clinias</hi> weeping, ſaid. O <hi>Socrates,</hi> the preſent time requireth, that wee ſhould ſhew foorth that Wiſedome which you haue alwayes ſpoken of to vs: for my Father is vexed with a ſodaine and intollerable Diſeaſe; and ſeemeth to be euen at deaths
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:176301:85"/>doore, and to take it very vnpatiently: although in times paſt, hee was wont to mocke thoſe that feared death, as though they were afraid at the countenaunce of an imagined Spirit: Come (I pray you) and blame him, as you were wont, that he may eaſily beare neceſsitie: Goe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with vs, and togeather with others, doe a godly worke.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>So.</speaker>
               <p>You haue made me very deſirous, O <hi>Clinias!</hi> to do what I can, to fulfill your requeſt, eſpecially ſeeing the worke is holy, which you craue to be done; let vs therefore make haſt: for if the matter be ſo, it is time to make haſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
               <p>So ſoone as he ſhall ſee you, O <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> he ſhall begin to recouer: for it hath often hapned, that he in ſome ſort repented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>So.</speaker>
               <p>Then we went vnto him by the Walles, thorow the <hi>Peritoman</hi> Fieldes; for he dwelt night the Gates towardes the <hi>Amazones</hi> Pillar: And we found him ſound of limme, and ſtrong of body; but weake in minde, and greatly ſtanding need of comfort, and often times ſtaying to take breath, and fetching ſighes and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:176301:86"/>grones, with many teares, and clapping of his handes. Which when I ſaw; What now, <hi>Axiochus</hi> (ſaid I) Where is now that your old &amp; boaſted Conſtancie? Where are the perpetuall prayſes of Virtues? Where is your wonderfull magnitude and boldneſſe of Minde? For euen as an ill or ſluggiſh Wraſtler may in the wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Scoole appeare couragious till he come to try all; ſo haue you fainted and yeelded in this conflict. Why, conſider you not the order and courſe of Nature, ſeeing you are ſo worthy a man, and ſo well learned: and if no other thing, yet that you are an <hi>Athenian?</hi> Remember you not that vulgar and old worne Sentence, wherein it is ſayd, That this life is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Pilgrimage; &amp; that we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues rightly, &amp; with an equal minde, as wanderers in a ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and ſo come to that thing which is due and neceſſarie; not with a weake and feeble, but with a ioyfull and merrie minde. But this tender ſoftneſſe, is more meete for Infancie, then for riper age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axi.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe thinges, O <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſeeme rightly ſpoken: But I know not how
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:176301:86"/>thorow imminent dangers, theſe ſame moſt comfortable wordes of patient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding, doe ſliely vaniſh away, and are neglected: yea, there ariſeth a certaine repugnant extreame feare, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth my minde on euery ſide. Oh alas, I ſhalbe depriude of this light, &amp; of theſe good thinges; I ſhall lie in darkneſſe: Hauing loſt my taſte and ſight, I ſhall rot in the earth, and be turned to Wormes and Duſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>So.</speaker>
               <p>Thou (ô <hi>Axiochus</hi>) doeſt ioyne Senſe with priuation of Senſe, without the diligent examination of Reaſon, and art contrary to thy ſelfe both in ſayings and doinges. Neither do you marke that you do both togeather complaine of the loſſe of your Senſes, and doe ſorrow for rottenneſſe and loſſe of good thinges; as though you being about to paſſe ouer into another life, ſhould rather flit into the priuation of euery Senſe: Priuation, I ſay, and that ſuch a one, as went before the time that you were borne. For as in the Common-weale of <hi>Draco</hi> and <hi>Caliſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes,</hi> no euill hath touched you; for you were one that was not compaſſed with
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:176301:87"/>euill: ſo after death, nothing ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart you; for you ſhall not be he, that may be inuironed with euill. Driue away therefore from you, all ſuch like triflings, and conſider thus much, that that being diſſolued which was compounded, and the Soule going vnto her owne place, this Body that remayneth, being earthly, and without reaſon, can by no meanes be Man: for we are a Soule, an Immortall liuing thing ſhut vp in a Mortall habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which Nature made vs as a ſhadow wherein to abide euill. Whereunto thoſe thinges that are ſweete, are Adulterous, filthy, naught, vaine, fading, and mixed, with many and ſundry miſeries, griefes, troubles, &amp; vexations. But thoſe things that are grieuous vnto it, are of their owne nature good, whole, ſound, and voyd of ſweetneſſe: Vnto it doe happen hot Tumors and Swellings, ſuperfluitie of Humours, decay of Senſes, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Bowels: Wherewith the Soule muſt needes be very much grieued and payned, being diffuſed and ſpread abroad through all the pores and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to bind and tie all thinges togeather.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:176301:87"/>Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that it now deſireth the life Celeſtiall, and nieſt to it of nature, and thirſteth thereafter, and after the Quire ſupernall. For the looſing or departing out of this life, is a paſſage from an euill thing, vnto a good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axtoc.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing <hi>(Socrates)</hi> that you doe iudge this life to be euill, why doe you tarry or abide in it; eſpecially ſeeing you doe moſt of all meditate on theſe thinges, and are ateacher of others, and doeſt excell all the reſt in minde &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly virtues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soc.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Axiochus,</hi> you are no ſufficient witneſſe for me, but do thinke &amp; eſteeme as doe the people of <hi>Athens.</hi> But I would very gladly, and wiſh in my heart, to haue the knowledge of theſe common thinges, and not to know thinges ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and vaine. Thoſe workes which we ſpake of, are the declamations of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus</hi> the Wiſe-man, ſome bought for ſixe pence, ſome two groates, and ſome foure; for verily he teacheth nothing of free coſt; and hath alwayes in his mouth that ſaying of <hi>Epicharmus, Manus manum lauat; dans aliquid aliquid accipe:</hi> i. <hi>The
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:176301:88"/>one hand waſheth the other: giue ſome thing, and take ſome thing:</hi> Meaning, that one Good turne asketh another. On the former dayes, when in the houſe of <hi>Callias</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hippomous,</hi> he declaymed, he brought in ſo many thinges againſt life, that it wanted but a litle, but I euen then, ended my life: and from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (ô <hi>Axiochus</hi>) my Minde doth die continually.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axt.</speaker>
               <p>What then are thoſe things that he there ſayd? I will rehearſe them all, ſo farre foorth as my memorie will ſerue mee: and thus he ſayd.</p>
               <p>What part of life is not full of euilles? Doth not the Infant yet ſcarcely borne, foorth-with waile and weepe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth it life with ſorrow; neither is there any griefe wanting, but cryeth and weepeth either for Parentes, or want of neceſſaries, or for cold, or for heat, or for hurtes? He cannot yet in words tell what he ayleth: he weepeth, and cryeth with voyce; onely voyce hath he without wordes, as a ſigne of griefe which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth. Now when he hath fulfilled the ſeauenth yeare of his age, he is troubled
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:176301:88"/>and turmoylad with very many labours; for then come vp Schoolemaiſters and Teachers, Alphabetaries and Gramari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with ſuch others, and doe beare rule ouer him none otherwiſe then a Tyrant. Then when he is ſome-what more gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, Cenſores of Arithmeticke, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributors of Geometrie, and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maiſters beſides theſe, doe beare rule ouer him. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is become a ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then doth Feare circumuent him: the Vniuerſitie, Prentiſhip, Sceptres, and the immoderate flowing and rage of euils doe diſpoſſeſſe him of the pleaſures wherein his heart delighteth. All the time and courſe of his youth, he is kept in, &amp; holden vnder by the Cenſorers of Manners, and abideth the ſentence of moſt ſeuere and vncorrupted Iudges. And when he is freed or looſed from their ſentence, then Care, Conſultations, &amp; aduiſements, come creeping vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him while he reaſoneth &amp; diſcourſeth within himſelfe, what path and courſe of life is beſt for him to follow: ſo that by the compariſon of the laboures and troubles that are to come, thoſe that are paſt, doe
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:176301:89"/>ſeeme both light, and onely to be feared of Infantes: For then ariſe expeditions of Warre, and Woundes, and often Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miges, Conflictes, and Battailes. At the length, old wrinckled crooking Age creepeth vpon him; vpon the which, there altogeather floweth euery foule, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, and vncureable euill of Nature; as a Banker looketh for aduantage, Nature requireth her Pledges, of this man, Sight; of that man, Hearing; of an other, them both: which if any doe reſtore, then doth he diſſolue, waxe weake, lame, may med, and impotent. Many liue euen to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt boundes of Old age; but then they are in minde, twiſe Children, fond, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepite: Wherefore, God in prouiding for Mans matters, doth in a ſhort time, call againe vnto himſelfe, thoſe whom he loueth. Therefore <hi>Agamedes</hi> and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonius,</hi> when they went vnto the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the God <hi>Apollo,</hi> and had prayed for that thing which is the beſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſtraight way fell ſo faſt aſleepe, that they neuer wakened after. The ſame alſo happened vnto the Prieſtes of <hi>luno</hi> in the Citie <hi>Argos,</hi> when their Mother
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:176301:89"/>had prayed for ſome good gift to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to her Sonnes.</p>
               <p>It ſhould be prolixious and tedious to rehearſe the ſentences of Poets, who in diuine &amp; heauenly Poeſies, doe deplore the Calamities of humaine life. I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe one notable and famous Poet, that ſpeaketh to this purpoſe, in theſe wordes. The Gods haue decreed, that miſerable mortall men ſhould liue in perpetuall ſorrow: Neither is there any thing vpon the earth, more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, then man. Therefore (they ſay) that <hi>Amphirarus</hi> was choſen of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> with a wonderfull great affect; and yet notwithſtanding he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not to the age of an Old man. And what doſt thou thinke of him, who biddeth him that is new borne, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the miſerie of his owne life? But I will now leaue off, leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to ſtray and wander wider and farther, then my purpoſe was. Who is there (I pray you) that doth not greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of that Studie, Art, Science, Trade, and Courſe of life, which himſelfe hath choſen? Handicrafts-men, Hyrelinges,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:176301:90"/>and ſuch, let vs view and conſider them a litle, that ſit vp labouring and toyling night by night, and doe ſcarcely get thinges neceſſarie for their liuing. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, day and night doe they, their wiues and children, liue full of complaintes, and fill all the houſe with weeping &amp; teares. What ſhall I ſay of Mariners, how many dangers are they hourely in? Rightly (in ſooth) did <hi>Bias</hi> count Marriners in the number neither of thoſe that are dead, nor of thoſe that are aliue: For they being earthly men, are in a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful-wiſe partakers of either eſtate. But Husbandry is ſweete: let it be ſo; but hath it not alwayes found occaſion of Sorrow? For in trueth, the Husbandman ſometime accuſeth, findeth fault with, and bewayleth Drought, ſometime ſhowers and Raine, ſometime Heate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſtions and parching burning Sunne, ſometimes extreamitie of Cold, and ſuch vnſeaſonable weather: ſometime Wormes, Caterpillers, Graſhoppers, and ſuch like deuowrers. What; Is not the Common-wealth in ſafetie and quiet? Truely it is honourable: But with how
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:176301:90"/>many euilles and ſorrowes is it turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? Truely it hath a certaine moouing, ſoft pleaſant ſwelling, deceiueable and troublous ioy, euen like to ſwelling and boyling Cholar: but a loſſe ſorrowfull and worſe then a thouſand deathes. For who can be happy, when there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, but he muſt needes liue at the peoples becke? And he is mocked and hiſſed at, as though he were a Play or a Fable of the people, berated, flouted, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miſerable and wretched.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soc.</speaker>
               <p>Where (ô ciuill <hi>Axiochus</hi>) dyed <hi>Melchindes?</hi> Where <hi>Thomiſtocles?</hi> Where <hi>Ephialtes?</hi> Where all the other Captaines? Theſe thinges verily I neuer thirſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Neither doth it ſeeme to be an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing, to execute the Magiſtrates duetie amongſt the madde multitude. But thoſe waitelayers that about <hi>Thera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes</hi> and <hi>Calixenus</hi> did the day after, bring vnder the Iudges or Rulers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the men vndiſcreetly to death, whom you <hi>Axiouchus</hi> togeather with <hi>Triptolamus</hi> did repugne in three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſpeaches vnto the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axioc.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay true, ô <hi>Socrates;</hi> And
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:176301:91"/>therefore from that ſame time, euen vntill this day, I haue euer eſchewed the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunalſhippe. Neither doth any thing ſeeme more difficile and hard, then the gouernement of the Common-weale. This is very plaine and well knowne to them, who themſelues haue to doe in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill matters. But you doe ſo ſpeake of theſe thinges, as one that a farre off, did ſee them out of a Glaſſe, or from the top of a Rocke, or the proſpect of a faire Tower. But my ſelfe doe right well know them, ſeeing I was my ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the matter. For verily the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort (O <hi>Socratus</hi> my friende,) is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, full of mockes and ſcornes, vaine, ſoone angried, cruel, enuious, rude, heaped full of troubles and trifles: and whoſeuer doth familiarly acquaint himſelfe with them, &amp; conuerſe amongſt them, doth at the length, become farre more miſerable then they be themſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing then (O <hi>Axiochus</hi>) you doe iudge, that this Diſcipline is aboue all other, moſt to be eſchewed; What doe you thinke of others? Are not they alſo to be fledde from? I haue further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:176301:91"/>more heard <hi>Prodicus,</hi> when once he ſaid, that Death doth not belong neither to the dead, nor to thoſe that are aliue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axi.</speaker>
               <p>Which way (O <hi>Socrates,</hi>) or in what manner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Socr.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe Death is not about the liuing: and the dead are not or haue no beeing: Wherefore, neither is Death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you <hi>Axiochus;</hi> becauſe you are not yet dead: neither if you depart this life, ſhall Death be about you; becauſe you ſhall not bee. Therefore griefe ſhould be vaine, if <hi>Axiochus</hi> doe bewaile that, which is not about <hi>Axiochus,</hi> neither ſhalbe hereafter: For you doe in like manner, as if you were afraide of <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Centaurus,</hi> when as theſe Monſters are neither now about you, neither ſhall be at any time hereafter. For that which is horrible and to be feared, happeneth to thoſe which are: But to thoſe which are not, nothing is to be feared.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axi.</speaker>
               <p>You gather theſe thinges, out of that light &amp; vaine babling, which is now common all abroad amongſt the vulgar ſort: For from amongſt them, commeth this copie of vaine wordes, compoſed
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:176301:92"/>for young mens ſakes. But I, who am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the good thinges of this life, doe ſtill mourne; although you haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in your Diſcourſe brought very ſtrong reaſons: For my ſorrowing head, doth not vnderſtand the fineneſſe of your wordes, neither diſcerne the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of your ſpeach. Although it heare the pompe and ſhining of ſpeach, yet it neglecteth, and is farte away from the trueth: neither can it abide thoſe rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed captious Sophiſmes; it onely atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on thoſe thinges which can knocke vpon, and pearce the Minde and Soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>So.</speaker>
               <p>Without reaſon <hi>(Axiochus,)</hi> doe you ioyne togeather the ſenſe of euill thinges, and the priuation of good thinges: And this lyeth cloſely hidden, that he indeed is dead who is depriued of good thinges, the paſsion of euill thinges afflicteth the contraries. But hee that is not, can neither marke or regard the orbitie or priuation. By what meanes therefore where there is wanting the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the things afflicting, can there be affliction? For vnleſſe in the beginning you ſhould put a certaine ſenſes by Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:176301:92"/>you ſhould be afray de of Death. But now you peruert and fore turmoyle your ſelfe, fearing leaſt you ſhould looſe your Soule. But you doe condemne your Soule to amiſsion, that it ſhalbe loſt, and not had againe; you feare leaſt Senſe ſhould be taken from you; and doeſt thinke that Senſe exiſting, cannot be comprehended of that Senſe, whereas there are many, and thoſe notable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Immortalitie of the Soule. For neither had Mortall nature riſen to ſo great excellencie, that it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the violence of outragious Beaſts, ſayle and paſſe ouer the Sea, build Cities, preſcribe order to Common-weales, looke vp into Heauen, meaſure the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of the Starres, marke the progreſſe of the Sunne and Moone, and their ryſings and ſettinges, defectes moreouer, and ſwift reſtitutions Meridian, and double conuerſions; the ſeauen Starres, &amp; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in like manner, and Sommer; the flawes of Winde, and the force of Raine and Stormie weather, the tempoſtions whurring Whorlewinde, and flaſhing of the Lightning; and to conclude, how
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:176301:93"/>the paſsions of the world ſhould ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ſtande in eternitie, vnleſſe there were in the Minde, ſome Diuine ſpirit, by which it ſhould get the intelligence of ſo great thinges. Wherefore, ô my deare <hi>Axiochus,</hi> you doe not flit vnto Death, but vnto Immortalitie it ſelfe. Neither ſhall good thinges be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from: but you ſhall enioy the ſound poſſeſsion of good thinges. Neither ſhall you and more receiue and enioy Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure mixt with a mortall Body: but ſhall quite be ſet free, and vtterly voyde of euery ſorrow: Thither (I ſay) you ſhall goe free from this Priſon; where you ſhall haue all thinges quiet, and remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from ſorrowfull Old age: Where the exultation and reioycing of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is an holy ioy, and their life hath no conuerſing with euilles; but is quiet, and nouriſhed with Peace; viewing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thinges, and contemplating the hidden ſecrets of Philoſophie; not veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto the grace of the multitude, or Theatre; but to the obiect of perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axio.</speaker>
               <p>Your Oration hath drawne my
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:176301:93"/>Minde, and mooued mee to affect the contrarie to that it did before. I am now quite changed: for I now doe not feare Death, but doe wiſh it. But as it is the manner of Rethoricians, I alſo aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, will expreſſe ſome thing. For now (ô <hi>Socrates,</hi>) I am caried from hence vp on high, and doe run thorow the Diuine circuite and heauenly Throne. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuered out of this Weakeneſſe, I am renewed ſo, that I am become alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather new, nothing that I was before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soc.</speaker>
               <p>I will alſo ſhew and declare vnto you (if it pleaſe you,) what <hi>Gobrias</hi> the Magian did teach mee. For (ſayd hee) at that time when as <hi>Xerxes</hi> paſſed into <hi>Greece</hi> with an Armie, his Grandfather (<hi>Gobrias</hi> by name,) was ſent into <hi>Delos,</hi> to keepe the Ile; werein, there were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant two Gods; where he ſayd: That of certaine Braſen Tables, which <hi>Opis</hi> and <hi>Hecaergos</hi> brought out of the North partes, that he learned, that in the ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body, the Soule doth flit into a hidden place vnder the Earth, wherein is the Kingdome of <hi>Juno,</hi> not a ſtraiter Haule of <hi>Iupiter;</hi> becauſe the Earth muſt
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:176301:94"/>holde the middle of the World; &amp; that muſt be the ſphericall heauen, whoſe one Hemiſphere, the Gods and Saintes doe enioy: The other, the Inferiours, partly Breathren of the heauenly Saintes, partly the children of the Brethren: But the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without, are the Prouinces of <hi>Pluto;</hi> which are bound and enuironed with Walles, Rayles, Barres, and Chaynes of Iron. Firſt doth the Riuer <hi>Acheron</hi> part theſe places inſunder; and then the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Cocytus</hi> doth ſeparate them: which when ſilly Soules haue paſſed ouer, they muſt needes be brought before the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudges, <hi>Minos</hi> and <hi>Radamanthus;</hi> to wit, into that Region which is called, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritatis Campus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>The Field of Trueth:</hi>
                  </hi> Where they ſitte in Iudgement, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the life of euery one that commeth vnto them. Heere no man can boulſter or defend himſelfe with lyes. Whoſoeuer then hath been ledde heere in this life by the good Spirit, doe paſſe ouer into the place of the Godly; where the Spring laſteth euer, and aboundeth with Fruites of euery kind, and floweth with Springs of moſt cleare and ſhining Waters, and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:176301:94"/>Meadowes moreouer very pleaſant, and bedecked with faire floriſhing Flowers of ſundry colours, and ſweete ſmelling ſauours: Neither is there wanting the fellowſhip of Philoſophers, nor Theatre of Poets. There are the companie of Singing-men and Quiriſters: There is Muſicke, Singinges, and ſweete Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, Pleaſant Bankets, and Holy and often Meetinges, inuiolable ioy of Drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and ſweete liuing togeather. There is no exceſſe of Heate or cold; but the nature of the Ayre is holeſome, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with light beames of the Sunne. Here are the Seates of purged Soules, where they celebrate the Diuine myſteries. What then hindreth, but that there may be giuen vnto you, firſt honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſeeing you deriue your originall from God? Contrarily, thoſe that haue defyled their liues with wickedneſſe, are of the Holliſh furies, ſodainely ſnatched through Hell into <hi>Chaos</hi> and <hi>Herebus,</hi> the deepeſt Pit of all: where lyeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of the Wicked, and the vaine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the Daughters of <hi>Danaeus;</hi> who in vaine doe labour to fill the Tunne
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:176301:95"/>with water, out of whoſe ſides filled full of holes, the water runneth ſo faſt, as they put it in; where is the thirſt of <hi>Tantulus,</hi> the bowels of <hi>Titius,</hi> the perpetuall row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Stone of <hi>Siſyphus:</hi> Whereas raging wild Beaſtes, byting Wormes, and ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Serpentrs doe inſeparably fould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Bodyes: Where inextinguible Firebrandes that can neuer be put out, doe burne vp their fleſh: Where wicked men are puniſhed with all kind of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and are for euer-more vexed with perpetuall paine. Theſe thinges, I heard of <hi>Gobrias.</hi> But you, O <hi>Axiochus,</hi> ſhall iudge of theſe thinges: for I being conſtrayned by reaſon, doe plainely and firmely know this onely, that euery Soule remayneth Immortall; and that that which goeth pure from theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, doe liue without ſorrowfulneſſe. Wherefore, O <hi>Axiochus,</hi> whether you goe vpward or downeward, it can none otherwiſe be, but you muſt needes be bleſſed, if ſo be you doe liue holily and godlily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Axi.</speaker>
               <p>I am aſhamed, ô my deare friend <hi>Socrates,</hi> and it abaſheth mee to ſpeake
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:176301:95"/>any further. The feare of Death is ſo farre from mee now, that I now doe moſt earneſtly deſire to die. Your former ſpeach, as though it were a Celeſtiall and Heauenly Oracle, hath ſo perſwaded mee. Now therefore, I doe deſpiſe this life, ſeeing that I am about to goe into a better, &amp; more deſired place: Wherefore theſe thinges that are thus ſpoken, I will quietly marke, ponder, and meditate by my ſelfe. And you, ô <hi>Socrates,</hi> I pray you come againe vnto me at afternoone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soc.</speaker>
               <p>I will doe as you ſay: But I will now returne againe vnto <hi>Cynoſarges,</hi> to walke there fore my recreation, from whence I was brought hither vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Heere endeth <hi>Xenocrates</hi> Booke concerning Death.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mecaenas good, I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raue of thee, my Patron for to bee;</l>
               <l>Gainſt carping Zoilus cankred corps, and cenſures bad of mee.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>W. White,</hi> for <hi>R. Bolton</hi> and <hi>W. White.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
